<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unknown being of the spirit, soul, and body, anatomized wherein very many Scriptures falsly translated, and corruptly interpreted are clearly explained, by which, many doctrines now taught that subvert the faith of the gospel are discovered / written by him that is unworthy to be a witness of divine truth, John Brayne.</title>
            <author>Brayne, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4334</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11724250</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11724250</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48357</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29283)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48357)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 16:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unknown being of the spirit, soul, and body, anatomized wherein very many Scriptures falsly translated, and corruptly interpreted are clearly explained, by which, many doctrines now taught that subvert the faith of the gospel are discovered / written by him that is unworthy to be a witness of divine truth, John Brayne.</title>
                  <author>Brayne, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Moon ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spirit.</term>
               <term>Soul.</term>
               <term>Flesh (Theology)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48357:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48357:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE UNKNOWN BEING OF THE Spirit, Soul, and Body; ANATOMIZED.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Very many Scriptures falſly Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and corruptly Interpreted, are clearly Explained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By which, many Doctrines now taught that ſubvert the Faith of the Goſpel, are diſcovered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by him that is unworthy to be a Witneſs of Divine Truth, JOHN BRAYNE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Moon</hi> at the Seven Stars in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, near the great North-door. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48357:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48357:2"/>
            <head>TO My very Noble Friend Colonel John Pine.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our being avocated from bearing the Burthen of the People, which for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares in the Two late Parliaments, and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Truſt, firſt and laſt lay on you, invited me to commend this inſuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe to you; As ſerving much to make a Man wiſe in leading him to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Himſelfe; Not after the way
<pb facs="tcp:48357:3"/>of the Schools, but of God, in which the uſe of Chriſt is rightly knowne, and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion clearly ſeen according to the Grace of God, and Jeſus Chriſt, in the Goſpell; To which high Myſtery I commend you, to direct your choiceſt Thoughts, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, to ſerve and honor you in the Work of the LORD. JOHN BRAYNE.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>January the 18th. <hi>1653.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48357:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERY OF THE Unknown Being of the Spirit and Soul of Man.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe I finde that the darkneſs occaſioned by the not right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of Man in his true nature of Being is very great, the Scriptures ſtrangely vailed, the Doctrine taught wonderfully corrupted, and the right uſe of Chriſt detained from the ſpirits of men; I thought my ſelf bound to publiſh this enſuing Treatiſe, the ground whereof I lay down in the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23. <hi>The very God of peace ſanctifie you wholly; and I pray God your whole ſpirit, and ſoul, and body be preſerved, &amp;c.</hi> In the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this is indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, if ye take away and divide any part of theſe, it is only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Of which, ſaith <hi>Ireneus,</hi> Lib. 5. cap. 1. <hi>Neque enim plaſmatio carnis ipſa ſecundum ſe homo perfectus eſt, ſed corpus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis &amp; pars hominis; neque anima ipſa ſecundum ſe homo, ſed anima hominis &amp; pars hominis; neque ſpiritus homo, ſpiritus enim &amp; non homo vocatur; commixtio autem &amp; unitio horum omnium perfectum hominem efficit; &amp; propter hoc Apoſtolus ſeipſum exponens, explanavit perfectam &amp; ſpiritualem ſalutem hominis in</hi> I <hi>ad</hi> Theſſ. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 23, <hi>&amp;c. Vide</hi> Auguſt. <hi>lib. queſt. cap.</hi> 67.</p>
            <p>Theſe three before, the Spirit, Soul and Body, are three diſtinct eſſential parts of Man, which I ſhall ſpeak in order particularly unto. But before I do that, it is neceſſary I ſhould ſhew you how the life and the breath in Man are diſtinguiſhed by God in the Scripture, which will ſhew us, that men need not (that have the Word of God) to go to <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato, &amp;c.</hi> to learn Philoſophy; they were in the dark, and knew it not; a thing in time God will purge out of this Nation, it being forbid in the Word by God expreſly, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.3. <hi>Ye ſhall not do after the doings of</hi> Egypt <hi>and</hi> Canaan, <hi>nor walk in thier Ordinances:</hi> Levit. 20.23. <hi>Ye ſhall not walk
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48357:4"/>in the manners of the Nations I caſt out</hi> Hence the houſes of learning ſet up among the Jews were houſes of the Prophets, that is, ſuch houſes in which the Prophets were firſt taught to be read and written, and then underſtood; and other learning then this God allowed not, nor doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his own people; and other houſes then theſe are not houſes of the Prophets, whoſe Students by an Hebraiſm are called <hi>children of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> 2 <hi>King</hi> 4.38. as thoſe ſtudy the Heathens are the ſons of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle: Matt.</hi> 11.15.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We need know no more then is in the Word, that is onely neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Word things are more excellently layd down, then in all the writings of the world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That is full of Truth; <hi>Ariſtotle, Ovid, &amp;c.</hi> full of Corruption, and Error, and Atheiſm; fit to make Atheiſts (as all by Nature are) more A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical, corrupting them in their minds at the firſt receiving of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt <hi>Solom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Word is light, Philoſophy of the Heathens darkneſs.</p>
            <p>1. The Soul and the Life are diſtinguiſhed,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.19. <hi>To deliver their Soul from death, and keep them alive in famine:</hi> Vatablus Hebraiſmus eſt pro ſervet eos in vita. Thus <hi>Pſa.</hi> 49.18. <hi>He bleſſed his Soul in his life:</hi> in which are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Job.</hi> 33.18. <hi>He keepeth back</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>his ſoul from the pit, and</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>his life from periſhing by the ſword.</hi> Verſ. 20. <hi>His life abhorreth bread, and his ſoul deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rable meat.</hi> Verſ. 22. <hi>His ſoul draweth neer to the grave, and his life to the deſtroyers.</hi> The Seventy render them by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Verſ. 28. <hi>He will deliver his ſoul from going into the pit, and his life ſhall ſee the light.</hi> Vide Verſ. 30.</p>
            <p>The ſpirit of man from the Spirit of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p>The Life and the Breath are diſtinguiſhed,</p>
            <p>Acts 17.25. <hi>God that giveth</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to all life, and breath, and all things.</hi> Rom. 8.2. Rev. 11.11.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Note here, As the Soul and Life are diſtinguiſhed in words and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Prophets, ſo Life and Breath by the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Life by <hi>James</hi> is ſet forth as a far inferior thing to the Soul: <hi>James</hi> 4.13, 14. ſpeaks againſt mens preſumptuous dependance on the Being of their life: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; What is your life? for it is but a vapor for a little time appearing, and after that it vaniſheth: This cannot be ſaid of the Soul, nor of the breath. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.33.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here in this ye have ſuch a definition of life, as all the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotelists</hi> on Earth cannot exceed, nor on like grounds attain unto,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48357:4"/>but in compariſon of this theirs is vain Philoſophy.</p>
            <p>This being undeniable truth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is matter ariſeth hence of exceeding great note and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all men, which is the groſs corrupting of the Word of God in the falſe tranſlating of it; the Tranſlators putting down in a hundred places neer, <hi>life</hi> for <hi>ſoul,</hi> rendering <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>life,</hi> and ſometimes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſoul,</hi> which ought not to be; the word and ſence is deſtroyed by it, and falſe Doctrine taught to the people: wherefore in eſpecial there is an extream neceſſity for another Tranſlation to be publiſhed, and this called in: The Old Teſtament in this particular is better tranſlated then the New, though ſome ſuch is in the Old, as that the minde of God is no way expreſſed, but clear contrary things, as one eſpecial place I have expounded, and fitted for the Preſs to publiſh, but had not where with to do it, which is of high concernment to the people of God, and for the Opening of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Breath is as a ligament by which Soul, Spirit and Body are kept together, and is one both that the Beaſt and Man enjoyeth.</p>
            <p>Theſe places, and many more in our Tranſlations, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>ſoul,</hi> have <hi>life</hi> put in them, againſt the <hi>Syriac,</hi> and the <hi>Arabic,</hi> which retain the <hi>Hebrew</hi> root <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in their Tranſlations. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.25. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.39. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.25. <hi>Mark</hi> 8.35. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.33. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.56. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.26. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.11.15.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.38, 39. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.13. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 27.10, 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.4. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> If the <hi>ſoul</hi> and <hi>life</hi> are two diſtinct things in Man, then to write <hi>life</hi> where God writes <hi>ſoul,</hi> is a preſumptuous deſtruction of the Truth of God: and the natural life in Chriſt is the ſame with that in us, he being in all things like us, ſin onely excepted.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>ſpirit, ſoul</hi> and <hi>body</hi> are three diſtinct parts of Man, I commend theſe Scriptures to you.</p>
            <p>Note how God ſpeaks to us of himſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>My Spirit, and my Soul.</hi> Mat. 12.18. <hi>My Soul.</hi> Mat. 10. <hi>As having a Body.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23. as before, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Luk. 1.46, 47. <hi>Mary ſaid</hi> (there is the body) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie the Lord, and</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>my ſpirit hath rejoyced in God my Saviour.</hi> Job 12.10. <hi>For in his hand is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the ſoul of every one</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>living, and</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the ſpirit of every fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (or <hi>all mankinde,</hi>) which is the <hi>Adam ſoma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In reſpect the Scripture ſaith, that every truth is confirmed und r two or three witneſſes, and here <hi>Paul, Mary, Job</hi> are produced, which is the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48357:5"/>number required, I ſhall proceed to particulars; and firſt of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.33. Chriſts Spirit is troubled, which was his humane ſpirit: And <hi>Cap.</hi> 13.21. of his Soul: <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.27. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>The Spirit is not by propagation conveyed from man to man: <hi>Job</hi> 26. verſ. 4. <hi>Whoſe ſpirit came from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt thing neceſſary to be conſidered is the Being and Beginning of the Spirit, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 2.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Plaſmavit,</hi> the word reſpects the forming of a thing out of a groſs body, as a Potter of the clay his veſſel, ſo God formed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Adam</hi> of the duſt of the Earth, when he breathed in his face <hi>ſpiraculum vitarum,</hi> the breath of lives (not of life, as the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Tranſlations read, but lives in the plural, <hi>viz.</hi> that of the <hi>ſoul,</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi>) and the <hi>Adam,</hi> the Earth, became <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which I thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, And the Earth IS to the Soul <hi>(vivens)</hi> living, where the Soul and the life are diſtinguiſhed, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 38.19. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.21, 22. <hi>Numb.</hi> 31.40.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>the Lord breathed into Adam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is lives in the plural, not <hi>life,</hi> as it is corruptly tranſlated, and admirably cleared, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57.16. the <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>ſpiration,</hi> ſhewing,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God placed in man differing lives.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>ſpirit</hi> hath its life, the <hi>ſoul</hi> its, and the <hi>body</hi> its, by this Breath.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All were far differently from the beaſts by God communicated to man in his Creation, as I ſhall ſhew hereafter, <hi>Job</hi> 35.</p>
            <p>Of this Life of the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As God of the ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>tohu</hi> and <hi>bohu,</hi> chaos and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, made Heaven and Earth, Man and Angels, Beaſts and Fiſhes; ſo of the ſame ſpiration or emiſſion he made life in the <hi>ſoul,</hi> the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> the <hi>body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As he divided between the waters above the Firmament, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters beneath; ſo he divided the ſoul life from that of the ſpirit, Man, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, having in himſelf, as the perfection of the Creation, that which correſponds to all theſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A darkneſs that lieth hereby on the ſpirits of men is removed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whereas God ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Adam ſhould dye in the day he eat of the tree of knowledg of good and evil;</hi> ſome expound ing the day by a thouſand years, others other-ways; but I forbear, and commend to you this, That God, in that day he ſpake to man, alluded to the natural day of man, not God; this ſentence was made good on him, not by taking away his <hi>ſoul-life,</hi> but his <hi>ſpirit-life,</hi> which was then dead in him, as appears, in that his acceſs to, &amp; familiarity with, and innocency before <hi>God,</hi> was loſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48357:5"/>together with all farther actings of the ſpirit within him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence, as <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.6. of the wanton widow, <hi>ſhe is dead whiles ſhe liveth,</hi> which ſhews, that ſhe was ſome way or where dead, that is, in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in ſome thing or part alive, which was in body and ſoul.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the ſpirit was dead, appears 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44. for Chriſt was made a quickening ſpirit to <hi>Adams</hi> generation, who by his fall became only a living ſoul, the ſpirit being dead in him; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14. this ſpoke to men alive in the fleſh, but dead in the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="6">6. This quickening of the ſpirit is the great work of Chriſt on man in the days of the Goſpel, to raiſe the ſpirit from its death, which is called <hi>the firſt Reſurrection, Rev.</hi> 20.6.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Thoſe that confound ſoul and ſpirit, do deſtroy the faith, and put men either to expect that now is to be done hereafter, or that hereafter is to be done now; indeed now is to be the reſurrection of the ſpirit by the Word and Spirit of Chriſt, or that at laſt will be nothing available; many Souls by this deluſion have been undone.</p>
            <p n="8">8. This death firſt entred into the world by <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, (ſo the reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this life is firſt,) and is called <hi>filthineſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</p>
            <p n="9">9. This reſurrection is by beleeving in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 11.25, 26.</p>
            <p n="10">10. As the ſoul is to the body, ſo the ſpirit is to the ſoul; the ſoul is in the blood as its ſeat, and the ſpirit in the mind as its ſeat, being the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limeſt part of the ſoul, informing and leading the ſoul and body.</p>
            <p>To make a definition of the Spirit no man ever could ſince the fall that was meer man: <hi>Solomon,</hi> whoſe Philoſophy exceeds all elſe that men call ſo, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Who knoweth the ſpirit of man that aſcendeth to ſupernals?</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that above and above of the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shewing that the ſpirit of man was of an unknown excellency; if any had known it of men, <hi>Solomon</hi> had: <hi>Adams</hi> death of ſpirit, was, that he loſt the knowledg of God, himſelf, and ſenſe of his Soul-miſery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Reſtoration thereof we have ſome diſcovery made of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thereof, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23. among which, Faith, that excellent grace is ſaid to be one, which, ſince the death of the ſpirit, is the gift of God, and a part of the ſpirits reſurrection and life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſpirit is that which is immortally with God, as in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. <hi>The ſpirit returns to God that gave it;</hi> and who dares ſay more returned, either that the Soul or life doth, and not be guilty of adding to the Word?</p>
            <p n="4">4. It was the Spirit Chriſt breathed out, and no more, and the Spirit he was ſo careful of to commit to the hands of God, and nothing elſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.50. <hi>Mark</hi> 15.37. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.46. all which Scriptures ſhew that nothing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48357:6"/>went forth of Chriſt at his death but his Spirit, and as not out of him, ſo not out of us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 78.39. <hi>&amp;</hi> 104.29. <hi>Judg.</hi> 15.19. And thus <hi>Stephen,</hi> Acts 7.59 <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit;</hi> had his Soul then left his body, he would have been as careful of the one as the other: See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. the ſpirit is with the Lord, the body dead.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As the ſpirits of juſt men are immediate with God, ſo unbeleevers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to God alſo, and receive the ſentence of condemnation, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to priſon: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18, 19, 20. <hi>But quickned in the ſpirit, by which he</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>went and preached to the ſpirit in priſon, that ſometime were diſobedient, in the days of Noah.</hi> 1. The ſpirits, not Souls not bodies, are in priſon, yea ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. 2. They are the ſpirits of thoſe bodies were diſobedient in the days of <hi>Noah</hi> at his preaching; ſo that what men falſly attribute to the Soul, is in truth by God in Scripture only ſaid of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſpirit is to be raiſed by the Spirit of Chriſt, not the Soul nor bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; <hi>John</hi> 6.63. <hi>The fleſh profiteth nothing, it is the ſpirit quickneth:</hi> So that the deluſion of the times takes off men from the true and immediate uſe of Chriſt and the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The ſpirit thus raiſed is that which God mainly reſpects in his ſervice; <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Thoſe that worſhip God, ſhall worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 14.15. <hi>If I ſing, I will ſing with the ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The ſpirit ſeems to be of an unknown excellency by what <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Though abſent in body, yet preſent in ſpirit:</hi> How the ſpirit may be preſent in the abſence of the body, and how the Apoſtle intends it, is a myſtery.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The ſeat of the ſpirit is the mind, which is the ſublimer part of the Soul, as the Soul in the blood the moſt excellent part of the body, (1.) That ſo it may have the more command and readier influence on the whole man, (2.) That being the next or neareſt to its ſelf in being &amp; in likeneſs, <hi>Ro.</hi> 12.2.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The converſe of God is with the ſpirit, as the ſpirit with the Soul, the fleſh and ſpirit are contrary; <hi>the fleſh</hi> in thoſe are ſanctified <hi>wars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Soul,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.22. <hi>Phil.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whereas men are the fathers of the fleſh and ſoul, God is the Father of ſpirits, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Every man hath a particular ſpirit; Chriſt as man calls his, <hi>my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; Stephen</hi> his, <hi>my ſpirit; Mary</hi> hers, her <hi>ſpirit,</hi> both male and female, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.27. <hi>Jacob</hi> his ſpirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p n="13">13. In this part of man it is the Apoſtle alludes unto, when he ſaith, that <hi>in Adam all dye,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. The actual ſins we after commit are not of <hi>Adam,</hi> though death of ſoul and body are annexed to it, <hi>Rom.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48357:6"/>
            <p>Death raigned over thoſe had not ſinned after <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion: <hi>Vide Acts</hi> 5.5, 10. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That every man, even wicked men, have each a diſtinct ſpirit, <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.30. ſee how the King of the <hi>Amorites</hi> is ſaid to have his ſpirit hardened, and heart obſtinate.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall be ſo blind as to deny this truth, ſee <hi>Job</hi> 32.7, 8. <hi>I ſaid, days ſhould ſpeak, and multitude of years ſhould ſpeak wiſdom: But there is a ſpirit in man, and the inspiration of the Almighty giveth them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi> 1 Cor. 6.17.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is not in days or years, or other acquired habits, that inables men to ſpeak profitably, effectually, feelingly, but the ſpirit in man makes a man more wiſe then his Teachers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Almighty, when the ſpirit is quickened, gives it underſtanding, which the Soul ſhould never have, or can have, from God; for the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>underſtandeth not the things of God, nor can he;</hi> but the ſpirit is taught of God the things <hi>eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor hath it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the heart of man to conſider.</hi> Acts 6.9, 10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence the regenerate man is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. of which <hi>Origen</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Puto quod conſuetudine ſua Apoſtolus utatur etiam in hoc loco, ſciens mediam ſemper eſſe animam inter ſpiritum &amp; carnem &amp; aut jungere ſe carni &amp; effici unum cum carne, aut ſociare ſe ſpiritui &amp; eſſe unum cum ſpiritu, ex qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſi quidem cum carne ſit carnales homines fiant, ſi vero cum ſpiritu ſpiritales &amp; idcirco extrinſecus eam non nominat ſed carnem tantum vel ſpiritum ſcit enim alteri horum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſario animam cohoerere ſicut in his ad quos dicit vos autem in carne non eſtis ſed in ſpiritu.</hi> Per Archon. Lib. 2. <hi>de anima,</hi> Orig. 32 Homil. <hi>John</hi> underſtands what is written of the fleſh and ſpirit in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. from verſ. 17, 23. is meant of our fleſh and our ſpirit, and not of the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Solomon</hi> gives the moſt clear deſcription of the ſpirit, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.27. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The candle or light of the Lord is the ſpirit of man,</hi> or the inſpiration of man; he alludes to what was done in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 1. Signifying, when man fell, this candle was put out. 2. When men are regenerated, the Lord lights it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.15. 3. The Conſcience is the remain of that light in man, of which <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>Job</hi> 18.6. <hi>The light ſhall be dark in his tabernacle,</hi> that is, his Conſcience within him ſhall be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht, <hi>Job</hi> 21.17. ſinning againſt the light of Conſcience, they put out the candle light: <hi>Job</hi> 29.3. <hi>When his candle</hi> the ſpirit <hi>ſhined on</hi> me, <hi>my head, by his light I ſhall paſs the darkneſs:</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.19. <hi>Quench not the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48357:7"/>5. This breathing of God into the face of man is a metaphorical expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, uſed of God for condeſcention to man, and commends to us ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate way God had to communicate himſelf to man, more then to the other of the terreſtrial Creatures, by which he was ſaid to be after the image and likeneſs of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. Epheſ.</hi> 2.18. <hi>There is one Spirit;</hi> ſo that men have not each a particular ſpirit in them; and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Resp.</hi> This is not ſpoke of the ſpirit of man, but God.</p>
            <p n="2">2, Nor as man a Creature, but a Chriſtian; all Beleevers had this Spirit, but no Unbeleevers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is not the ſpirit of man, but that Spirit is the Spirit to the ſpirit of man, and gives it life again as at firſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Of this it is ſaid, <hi>If any have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. Eccleſ.</hi> 3.19. Man and beaſts are ſaid to have one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, one ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here, is taken for wind, or breath, not ſpirit; he in the ſame place ſpeaks of the death of them both, in which they are one, though not in the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Verſ. 21. he comes again with the ſame word, and then diſtinguiſheth the beaſts ſpirit from mans, the one goeth up to higher beatitude and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the other deſcendeth to its firſt matter and being at its end.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The now ignorance of the Soul and ſpirit among men, ſufficiently ſhews what a vail of darkneſs is on the faces of the wiſe and prudent of the times, who cry down New Lights, becauſe in love with the old dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: The Philoſophers ſaying is uſeful, <hi>Noſce tei pſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. <hi>We are his off-spring.</hi> The Poet in this alludes to Gods breathing into man the breath of life, in which he came to ſpring off or from God, he having in him a likeneſs of God through the immortality of ſpirit, and its ſpirituality of nature with the other endowments of his Soul.</p>
            <p>The Soul and Spirit are ſo diſtinct,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That now the Soul feels not the death of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor when the Soul and body dye, doth the ſpirit feel any thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of pain, but the Soul only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> God at once breathed in Soul and ſpirit, therefore they are one.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are not one as in their names.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are ſaid to be lives begun in man at that one breathing, which muſt diſtinguiſh them in the effence &amp; being of them, and one muſt hereby be better or greater, more like God, and have more of God, then another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Be ye renewed in the ſpirit of your mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48357:7"/>1 In this yee have the ſeat of the ſpirit, which is the ſupream part of the Soul, <hi>Job</hi> 20.3. <hi>Datur homini ut maneat, &amp; quaſi caput ejus ſit. Ambroſe,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Its effects or acts there, are to ſpiritualize the mind, <hi>Romans</hi> 8.6.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ſurvay of man is of the ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. which now only doth remain in that obliterated fragment of the Conſcience in man.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The ſpirit under the Goſpel-ſtate in time of grace is to be renewed, this is the now work of God and Chriſt, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.5. in which he is born again.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The mind without the ſpirit to God, is as the body without the ſoule to man 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. the Spirit by the Word comes to purifie the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The carriage of man is from his ſpirit, as high ſpirited, meek, haſty, <hi>Elias</hi> ſpirit, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.55. <hi>Yee know not of what ſpirit ye are of.</hi> O but we know not we have any.</p>
            <p>Jude <hi>19.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſoule men, not having a ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The ſpirit being dead, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.13. they are ſaid not to be.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They wanting the light of the ſpirit, did corruptly corrupt the truth and way of God, and did their owne wills inſtead of Gods: ſetting up Churches, adminiſtring the Ordinances of God according to their ſence, not the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If any ſay theſe diſtinctions are made by me onely,</hi> I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>The Word of God is quicke, &amp;c. divides a ſunder the Soule and the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Yee ſee here is a Soul and Spirit.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The Word of God divides a ſunder theſe, and not confounds them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The Word ſhews what the Spirit is, and what the Soule is, and what Chriſt hath done for either; and will do in them, and ſhall be done to them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 No man hath the uſe, knowledge, or the underſtanding of the word of God, until he ſeeth how theſe are divided, and thereby divide the word aright to them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Thoſe that ſpeak againſt the dividing of them, ſeek to take away the edge of the Word, the life and power of it, and ſo to make it uſeleſſe to men.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Cor. 15.44. <hi>It is ſown</hi> (that is by birth) <hi>a ſoule body, it is raiſed</hi> (in the firſt reſurrection) <hi>a spirituall body; there is a ſoule body</hi> (the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48357:8"/>naturall man) <hi>and a spiritual</hi> (the regenerate) Ver 46. <hi>But the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall body is not firſt, but the ſoule body</hi> (the naturall man) <hi>and after the ſpiritual body</hi> (that is after regeneration.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ver.</hi> 47. clears this truth, <hi>The firſt man Adam was of the earth, the ſecond from heaven, vide</hi> ver. 48, 49.</p>
            <p>Vide 1 Cor. 2.15. <hi>The ſpirituall man judgeth all things, the naturall</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the ſoule man, underſtandeth not the things of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The divine nature of mans ſpirit appeares to be far above the ſoule, in that it hath not reſpect to creature delights as the ſoule hath, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Salomon</hi> of all found nothing but vanity and vexation of ſpirit; ſo that the ſpirit is vexed with the deluſions and deceipts, it ſeduces and wars againſt the poor ſoule, with 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 11.</p>
            <p>Gal. 5.17. <hi>The fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The fleſh luſteth for temporal food, and neglects ſpirituall; the ſpirit luſteth for ſpirituall, and neglects temporal, to keep under his body.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The fleſh and ſpirit are contrary, but not fleſh and ſoule in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, nor ſoule and ſpirit, in the regenerate man.</p>
            <p>Eccleſ. 8.8. <hi>No man hath power over the Spirit to retaine the Spirit, nor hath he power in the day of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words are thus to be read, no <hi>Adam</hi> (fleſh) hath power over the ſpirit for the reſtraining of it nor hath it power in the day of death.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Spirit is not under mans, but Gods authority.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Nor hath man in the day of death any thing to doe with the ſpirit, no not to Judgement: <hi>who art thou that judgeſt another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 So that what ignorantly is applied to the foule, that the Scriptures in the name of God applies to the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="4">4 This was excellently fulfilled in <hi>Paul,</hi> vide <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16. of the ſoule it is ſaid otherwiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Pet. 4.6. <hi>For this cauſe was the Goſpel preached to them that are dead: that they might be judged according to men in the fleſh, but live according to God in the ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The Goſpell, that is the Grace of Chriſt, is only to be preached to thoſe who are dead, that is, ſpiritually dead to the world and themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Speaking graciouſly to them, and of them in compaſſion to their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities as it is ſaid of God, <hi>he remembred that they were but fleſh,</hi> ſo God in the Goſpel ſpeaks to man as in fleſh, in weaknes and infirmities of body.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Yet that they ſhould live according to God in the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The Goſpell is to be preached to none but theſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Nor to no other end, but as before.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48357:8"/>
            <p>The death of the spirit in Man</p>
            <p n="1">1 Is in this excellently manifeſted, that man knows it not, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.21. <hi>who doth know the ſpirit of man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 That he is ſo inſenſible of it, that he knows not that he hath a ſpirit in him, but takes ſoule for ſpirit, and ſpirit for ſoule, nor can hee diſtinguiſh any operation of the ſpirit, diſtinct from the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If he doe, it is to place it in ſome inferior region in the body below the ſoule, as the animall, vitall, naturall; how far theſe are below the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and how far contrary to that God in his philoſophy ſpeaks, every man may judge.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Nor doth man miſſe the lack of its uſe and knowledge, ſo that his ſpirit indeed is not to him being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theoph.</hi> on 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. <hi>By the ſpirit of man underſtandeth the Spirit of God in man.</hi> Saith he, <hi>Spiritus, id eſt, donum quod per baptiſmum jam accepiſtis. Auguſtine</hi> on the words, <hi>Quid hic ſpiritum vocat, donum ſpiritus. Ambroſe</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>Ut integer ſit ſpiritus datus nobis:</hi> and after, <hi>ad hoc enim datur homini ut maneat, &amp; ſit quaſi caput ejus:</hi> In this whether he ſpeaks of it as of the Spirit of God or man, judge yee; But I take it as of man, if not, ſee into what a darkneſſe the world was fallen in, in four hundred years time after Chriſt, when men had loſt the light of the word, that diſcovered to them the being of the Spirit in them, and with it the right uſe of Chriſt in the time of grace, and what his work was, and whereon to be.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That the Spirit here is clear, a part of us, a part of the lot of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That this ſpirit is to be ſanctified as well as the body or ſoule, and needs ſanctification by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.21. and in many other places; <hi>Stephen</hi> ſaid, <hi>my ſpirit,</hi> not thy Spirit, <hi>Lord receive:</hi> and ſo <hi>Mary;</hi> who knoweth now indeed the ſpirit of man, when men know not that they have a ſpirit of their own within them? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.3.</p>
            <p>No wonder <hi>Auſtin</hi> and others run to philoſophy (having loſt the knowledge of the Spirit which was immortal) to prove the ſoule immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall againſt the Scripture: upon which philoſophicall hinges the Divinity of the now times are hanged, in which untruths, error, and deceipts are told the people, to the overthrow of hope, and ſhaking of faith in men, and deſtruction of the Truth: and in this follow not the Lords Spirit but their own, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>For the wind paſſeth over
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48357:9"/>it, and it is gone,</hi> which is a groſſe corrupting of the word by the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranſlating of it.</p>
            <p>In Ver. 15, The Prophet ſpeaks of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the ſorrowfull man,</hi> ſaying, <hi>for the Spirit was in him is departed, and he is not to us, his place ſhall know it no more,</hi> which is ſaid of the falne flower or ſoule of man, ſee the part of the ſoule in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.24.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Spirit God breathed into man is God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp. Amos</hi> 4.13. God is ſaid to create the ſpirit as other things and that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here is ſpirit, not wind; he after in the next words mentions <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>Heb. 4.12. <hi>Dividing between the ſpirit, and ſoule, and marrow, and bones, and joynts, and ſinews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The word divides between ſoul and ſpirit, which proves they are not by Gods word one and the ſame, as men after themſelves teach and affirm.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas other object, that it is but a dividing of the ſame thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by ſeverall tearms, as a dividing marrow, joynts, bones, which are all of the body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. <hi>It is granted, the ſoule and body are of different natures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The body indeed being a groſs corporeal ſubſtance may be divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt its ſeveral parts, but the ſoul being of a ſpiritual nature is individual.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ſpirit being more ſpiritually ſublime, is more unpoſſible to be divided then the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Nor is the ſpirit a part of the ſoule; no more then the ſoule is a part of the body; but far more exceeds the ſoule, then the ſoule the body.</p>
            <p>Exod. 21.23 <hi>If there be death</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (the word ſignifies murder) <hi>thou ſhalt give ſoule for ſoule,</hi> we corruptly read <hi>life for life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jerem.</hi> 38.15. <hi>As the Lord liveth made us this ſoule;</hi> but the <hi>ſpirit, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. is ſaid to be given of God, ſo that the being of one in man, is in a different way of being from the other.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It ſeems to me all the ſoules of men are but one ſoule divided, <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.7. and <hi>Act.</hi> 17.26. which is the ground of love, all being as one man, and ſo thy own fleſh, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 38.15.</p>
            <p>The firſt general of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>That every naturall man before regeneration is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe his ſpirit being dead in him, his ſoule is the moſt excellent part in being in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He is guided by the darke light of his ſoule, to act all, and only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording threunto.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:48357:9"/>3 He knows nothing higher then that of his ſoule is dictated to him; yea, nor can he receive, before his ſpirit be quickened, anything of a higher nature, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Rom. 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> In the Syr. and Arab. it is <hi>nephes,</hi> and <hi>Sultanan</hi> as the Heb.</p>
            <p>Note God ſpeaking of the ſpirit, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.8. Says no man hath power <hi>Schallit</hi> over the ſpirit, which the Greek 70 renders by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſhews the higheſt power was of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The ſoule and ſpirit are two.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They ſtrangely differ, one is ſubject, the other not to power.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That, that is ſubject to power, power can reach by the ſword, but the other that they cannot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the ſecond part of man <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſoule</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The excellency whereof is noted <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.22. <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.37.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In its creation or originall being, it was ſpired into man of God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, which proves ſufficiently it far exceeds the beaſts ſoule, which with the bodies had their being together from the earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ordinary way of continuance of the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It is not ſaid as of the Spirit that God gives it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 But of the contrary are ſaid to come out of the loyns of the parents, <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.26. <hi>Exod</hi> 1.5. <hi>vide Ezek.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not ſaid to return to God, but goe to the grave, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.27, 31. <hi>Job</hi> 33.18, 20, 22, 28, 30. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.15. and 94.17.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That with the body it is to partake of the reſurrection, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.31. ſeeing this before ſpake of the reſurrection of Chriſt, that his <hi>ſoule was not left in hell, nor his fleſh did not ſee corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Here are two parts, the fleſh and ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Theſe were in the grave.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Theſe had both intereſt in the reſurrection of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4 What was done in Chriſt, is to be done in Saints, becauſe done for them. Now of the ſoule of Chriſt 1. It is ſaid he poured out his ſoule to death, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He is ſaid to give his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſoule for his ſheep, <hi>John</hi> 10.11. ver. 15. he layeth it down, ver. 17. he ſaith, the father loved him becauſe he laid downe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> his ſoule. O did God love his Son for this? and ſhall this ſo great a cauſe of love be hid from us? Have not we much more cauſe to love him for it, and inquire into it, that it may be a cauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48357:10"/>of our love to him? alſo what need have our hearts to be ſtirred up there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. O know to lay down <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the life a vapour is nothing like this, to ingage Gods love to Chriſt, or mans either.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>in this we have knowne love, becauſe he laid downe his ſoule for us;</hi> as if without this laying downe of his ſoule, no ſoule can know his love, not in laying down of his life, or being man, &amp;c. <hi>Io.</hi> 15.13.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What Chriſt did, we may, and ought doe, by laying downe our ſouls for the brethren.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10. <hi>His ſoul was made an offering for ſin,</hi> in which we may ſee how far the ſoule of Chriſt acted in the work of our ſalvation, and how unable wee are to bee ſaved without it, and beleeving it, againſt all which, men oppoſe themſelves in theſe dayes.</p>
            <p n="6">6 His ſoule was in the grave, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.31.</p>
            <p n="7">7 He ſaith, <hi>his ſoule was heavy to the death,</hi> Math. 26.38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quer.</hi> If all this were done in Chriſts ſoul, whether our ſouls are not capable of, and lyable to the ſame things in this world, <hi>he was in all things tempted like us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Chriſt ſuffered in the fleſh for us,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1. <hi>and therefore not in his ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 His ſuffering in the fleſh, contains all thoſe ſorrows, afflictions, pains and torments, were laid on him before his death.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In his death, and death of ſoule was the laſt end of all his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The pouring of his ſoule out to death, was in the ſoul a ſuffering in a ſpeciall manner.</p>
            <p n="4">4 As he that ſaith Chriſt aſcended into Heaven with his body, in ſo ſaying, denies not he alſo aſcended into the heavens in his ſoule; ſo in ſaying Chriſt ſuffered in his fleſh, it is not denyed that he alſo ſuffered in his ſoule.</p>
            <p n="8">8 The ſoule and body of Chriſt being thus carryed home to the houſe of death, the grave, Chriſt by his Spirit and Almightineſſe redeems his ſoule, and in that others, deſtroying death, delivers the body from the grave, and the bonds thereof, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14.</p>
            <p n="9">9 The excellency of the ſoule <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.22. <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.37. <hi>what ſhall it advantage a man to gaine the whole world and loſe his owne ſoule, or what ſhall a man give in exchange for his ſoule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 If figurative ſpeeches would prove any thing, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.3. were ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall, where mens ſoules of the Antichriſtian eſtate are every one ſaid
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48357:10"/>to dye, which ſhews it concerns men of the falſe Church eſtate every one of them to mind their eſtates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.28. He gave <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>his ſoule a ranſome for many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The ſoule of Chriſt was the ranſome.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This ranſom was paid by death, or could not be paid, <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.45. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.11. <hi>They loved not their ſouls to death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 That is, they gave their ſouls to death.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This the word injoyns ſaying, <hi>he that ſaveth ſhall loſe his ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fleſhy nature of the ſoule is clear, in that it came out of the loyns by propagation, in that God ſaith, <hi>what ever is of the fleſh is fleſh,</hi> Joh. 3.6.</p>
            <p n="1">1 This is notably manifeſted in the ſeat of the ſoule, that it is in the blood, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.23. <hi>is not the ſoule more then meat, and the body then raiment?</hi> Math. 6.25. Luk. 12.22. <hi>Take no thought for your ſoule, what yee ſhall cate or what yee ſhall drinke,</hi> Eccleſ. 6.2, 3.</p>
            <p>Note 1. Rayment, that is proper to the body, that looks for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſoule, that minds meat and drink, careing for it as being very ſenſible of the lack thereof, and delighted in the injoyment of it, <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Prov.</hi> 27.7. <hi>The full ſoul loatheth the hony comb, but to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry ſoule every bitter thing is ſweet,</hi> Pſal. 107.5. <hi>Hungry and thirſty, their ſoules fainted in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note it is obſervable, God ſpeaking of ſpirituall hunger, he ſaith not <hi>he hath filled the hungry ſoul,</hi> but <hi>the hungry</hi> (only) <hi>with good things, Luk.</hi> 1.53. or as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.9. he diſtinguiſhes the ſoule <hi>hungring for goodneſſe,</hi> and that for meat and drink.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Job.</hi> 33.20. <hi>His life abhorreth bread, and his ſoule deſireable meat,</hi> the ſoul it longs for meats that are pleaſing to its appetite, in which is the ſenſuality of it.</p>
            <p>Note this is an emminent argument of the ſoules fleſhy nature, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectneſſe to mortality.</p>
            <p n="4">4 If the ſoule may live without, why ſaies the Lord to it, to take it off, <hi>your father knoweth that yee have need of theſe things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 Why doth he uſe this Argument to the ſoule, that it is more then food, as to the body that it is more then raiment; if the ſoules neceſſitys were not ſupplyed in the one, as the bodies in the other?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> of it, is becauſe the ſeat of the ſoule is in the blood, which is fed with food, meat and drinke.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.3. <hi>Shechems</hi> ſoule clave unto <hi>Dinah,</hi> which ſhews the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48357:11"/>terrene carnall nature of the ſoule being converſant about fleſhly things.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Fleſhly luſts war againſt the ſoule,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.11. <hi>here it ſeems the deſires of meat and drink are not of the ſoule, but the fleſh, here by wars againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. I beſeech you as Pilgrims and Strangers to be taken off from fleſhy luſts which war againſt the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Noting that the fleſhly luſts of the ſoule did oppoſe and hinder it from thoſe things, did more eſpecially concern it, which were offered to them by the Spirit, but care of eating and drinking would not give them leave.</p>
            <p>This is no more then what Chriſt did before, in ſaying, <hi>take no care what yee ſhall eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here in the fleſh they are but Pilgrims and ſtrangers to the world, and therefore the ſoul to ſeek ſatisfaction in theſe was againſt it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that he exhorts them to be taken off from them, ſhews the whole man, fleſh, body, and dead ſpirit were once all fixt upon it, and after quickening, troubled with it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And whereas the fleſh and ſpirit may ſay and object, why we muſt care for meat and drinke, theſe are ſo neceſſary that our ſoule cannot be without it.</p>
            <p>Note the Spirit of God makes as it were an anſwer to it, ſaying, the luſting after theſe things doe warre againſt the ſoule, and were enemies to it.</p>
            <p>And ſhewes that theſe things they ſhould have, without having their minds carryed after, and perplexed with care for them, as in <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.22.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It is uſuall that the mind of man is divided into carnall and ſpirituall; whiles it is ſet on cloath and food, it is carnal; when on God and Chriſt, ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>Note now, the ſoule of the regenerate is for ſpirituall things, but the ſouls care of food, wars againſt him in thoſe deſires of life God hath quickened in him, to kill and deſtroy them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It ſhews how the ſoule is affected with fleſhy things, the delights, ſweetneſſe, pleaſure, gaine, loſſe of them, and how the gay out-ſide things of the world are in its mind, being ſaid to be carnally minded, and men ſowing to the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Note <hi>Salomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 6.7. <hi>All the labour of the Adam is for his mouth, yet his ſoule is not ſatisfied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 In theſe words are the <hi>Adam</hi> body, and <hi>nephes</hi> the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">2 What the <hi>Adams</hi> labour is for, it is for his mouth, that is, meat to give it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48357:11"/>3 After it is in the mouth, then it comes to the ſoule, that is not ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with what the hands can get, either it is not ſweet enough, or good enough, or it hath not quantity enough for to keep him many years. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got one thouſand, why, it is not enough, it would have ten thouſand, yea, all the world, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.20. <hi>The eyes of man are never ſatisfied;</hi> the body ſerves an ill Maſter in the ſoule; it is like Death and Hell, whiles it is carnally minded; What ſhall I eate, what ſhall I drink, what ſhall I have to morrow, next yeare? he thought he had pleaſed his ſoule well, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.18, 19.</p>
            <p>Pſal. 66.9. <hi>He holdeth our ſoule in life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The ſoule and life are diſtinct.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſoule of all are held in life, or they would dye.</p>
            <p n="3">3 God it is holds our ſoule in life, and ſuffers not our feet, that is the bodily being to be moved, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 78.50. and 1.16.8. and 22.19.</p>
            <p>Eſter 7.3. <hi>She prayed for the ſoule of Ahaſuerus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pſal. 22.29. <hi>All they that goe down to the duſt ſhall bow before him, (and his ſoule is not living)</hi> or none can keep alive his own ſoule.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The body goeth down to the duſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They are ſaid as dying men to bowe and ſtoop to God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.4. <hi>vide Pagnine</hi> on <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ſoul that is not alive, none, when the body goeth to duſt, can keep alive his own ſoule.</p>
            <p n="4">4 This <hi>John</hi> 19.30. was fulfilled in Chriſt, <hi>he bowed the head, and gave up the ſpirit,</hi> man bows before he dyes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.33. and thence are ſtretched out after death.</p>
            <p>Acts 27.10. <hi>I perce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve that this voyage will be with hurt and much damage, not only of the lading of the ſhip, but alſo of our ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The ſoules were ſubject to loſſe and ruine, as ſhip and goods.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If the ſoule were immortall, then he would not have put the goods and ſoule in the ſame ſtate, as in ver. 22. there ſhall be no loſſe of any ſoule. that is, none ſhall die.</p>
            <p>Rom. 2.5.16. Shews in this chapter the day of Judgement is looked on and ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Ver. 6. <hi>When God renders to every man according to his deeds,</hi> Ver. 8, 9. <hi>Then on every ſoule that is contentious, and doth diſobey the truth, ſhall be tribulation and anguiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt ſhews that untill then the ſoul of man ſuffers none of theſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If it were immortall it ſhould doe as well as the ſpirit, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. which proves the ſpirit immortall, the ſoul mortall.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48357:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The next Generall that proves the mortality of the ſouls is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 That it is joyned, with the fleſh, and called fleſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That when diſ-joyned it is called blood, which pertains to fleſh, and divided by the word <hi>fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 <hi>The Scripture cals the Soule and Body fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gen. 6.3. <hi>My ſpirit ſhall not alwaies ſtrive with man, for that hee alſo is fleſh,</hi> the words may be better read thus, <hi>My ſpirit ſhall not ſtrive in man for ever, becauſe that he is fleſh,</hi> by which the 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. is only to be interpreted.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Note the ſpirit was dead, what elſe was in man was of a fleſhly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yea, God cals it fleſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Though he cals man <hi>Adam,</hi> as if he meant his body, yet after ſaying [<hi>hee</hi>] he comprehended ſoule and body, as all fleſh was in being in him.</p>
            <p n="3">3 While man is fleſh, there is but a ſtriving with them, and as it were an outſtanding by them of the ſpirit, called a reſiſting of the ſpirit, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, fall againſt the holy ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Matth. 26.41. <hi>The ſpirit is willing, the fleſh is weak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Fleſh and ſpirit are oppoſed onely, the ſoule not mentioned.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſoule is fleſhly in good men, not ſpiritual, and therefore is to be underſtood in fleſh, and not in the word ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whereas it ſaith <hi>weake</hi> only, it ſpeaks of the inclinations of the ſoul, not the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. <hi>In me, that is in my fleſh, dwels not any good thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>John 6.63. <hi>It is the ſpirit quickeneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Here are only two parts as before.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It ſignifies that where the ſpirit is not a quickening ſpirit, there the fleſh and ſoule profits not.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That the firſt reſurrection is of the ſpirit, the next of ſoule and body, and that of the ſoule and body, without this of the ſpirit profits not, but rather aggravates its miſery and woe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When it ſpeaks of the naturall man whoſe ſpirit is dead, and ſo is ſaid not to be, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.13. as <hi>Joſeph,</hi> whom his brethren thought was dead, is ſaid not to bee, ſo the ſpirit in naturall man being dead, hee is called by the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if he had no ſpirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. and 15.44. It is diſtinguiſhed by fleſh for the body, and ſoule for the blood: The Reaſons of it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48357:12"/>1 Blood is the ſoule of Beaſts, or the ſoule is ſaid to be in the blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Blood is the ſeat of the ſoule of man, it is called the blood ſoule, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.17. he that hath done violence to the blood ſoule, ſhall flye to the pit, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Here is violence to the blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That is done to the blood, is done to the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Note, In this is the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtinction of the ſoule of man and beaſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The beaſts blood and ſoule were together out of the earth at once.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Mans blood was out of the earth, but his ſoule by which that blood came to be inanimated was from God, yet the blood in man was the ſeat of the ſoule as in beaſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Yet in <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.5. It is ſpoken cloſely hereunto, thou ſhalt not eate the fleſh with his ſoule, his blood <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Which ſhewes the groſneſſe of the nature of the ſoule, and its fleſhy kind.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It ſhews how we are to underſtand the word blood when ſet down in oppoſition to, and diſtinguiſhed from the fleſh or body of man, and therefore called the blood of the ſoule, to ſhew, that when the blood was ſpoke of, the ſoule was intended thereby, not the body.</p>
            <p>Matth. 16.17. <hi>Fleſh and blood hath not revealed this to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 If by fleſh and blood be nothing elſe here intended, but that one part of man, his <hi>Adam,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, body, it is clear this without the ſpirit knowes nothing.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The ſoule man that hath body and ſoule, knows not the things of God, of which here the ſpirit ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Hence by fleſh I underſtand the body.</p>
            <p n="4">4 By blood the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Theſe two by any innate power of their own, or acquired habits, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not manifeſt to the ſpirit the myſtery of God, and ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The ſoul is ſo dead, that what it hath, it muſt have from fleſh and blood which is corruption, or from the father, it is in a ſtate of death, and all it hath is under the ſame, before Chriſt hath raiſed it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.40. <hi>Fleſh and blood ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 By <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> here is meant the Church, as it doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the diſpenſations of the ſpirit within, and of Chriſt in the Church Diſcipline without.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By fleſh, as before, is meant the body.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By blood, the ſoule of the naturall man.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48357:13"/>4 By theſe, untill the ſpirit be quickened, no man on ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> can lay claime to the Kingdome of God, but is by the inſtitution of God debarred it, and therefore faith, one of the fruits of the ſpirit in thoſe are quickened, is ſaid to be, that by which men were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Gal. 1.16. <hi>I conſulted not with fleſh and blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 [<hi>I</hi>] In his ſpirit now quickened, when the <hi>Adam</hi> had no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over it, to reſtrain it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This power is ſo far by the quickening of the ſpirit deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him, as that he immediately conſults not with it, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers it to be an enemy to Chriſt and his own felicity.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By fleſh and blood is meant his ſoul and body, who had before conſpired ſo together againſt the Lord and his truth.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The reveal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of Chriſt in him was the raiſing of his ſpirit from that death it lay in; as it was ſaid of Chriſt, he was revealed to be the Son of God by his raiſing from the dead, which in us is called the <hi>power of his reſurrection, Phil.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Cor. 5.16. <hi>We know no man according to the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 For blood it is ſaid clearly, God hath made all men of one blood, hence the prohibition in marriages did ariſe to prevent its confuſion. A thing of ſpeciall note,</p>
            <p n="2">2 The fleſh, which is of a more externall concernment.</p>
            <p n="1">1 He ſhews one man is not better according to the fleſh then an other, nor fitter for the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is prohibited by any prerogative it can have of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That it were the gifts of God, not the inward endowments of nature, or the outward beauty of the body was in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Goſpell to be reſpected.</p>
            <p>Heb. 2.14. <hi>For as much as the Children are partakers of fleſh and blood, be alſo himſelfe tooke part of the ſame, that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 By fleſh and blood the natural mans body and ſoule are in this place ſet out, of which Chriſt was a real partaker, <hi>being made like to us in all things, ſin only excepted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 As far as Chriſt was fleſh and blood, he ſuffered death.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By this death of his he <hi>deſtroyed him that had the power of death, which is the Devill,</hi> which death was the pouring out of his ſoule to death.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48357:13"/>4 Without the right underſtanding in what and how Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, no true, nor right uſe of his death can be made.</p>
            <p>The underſtanding of fleſh and blood in this ſence opens many hid Truths.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That when the ſpirit of God names the body, the ſoule is uſually added to it, when fleſh, then blood ſets out the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As fleſh and blood are together, ſo ſoule and body are, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Scripture dialect.</p>
            <p>Note, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſprinkling the people with the blood of the beaſts, called the blood of the Covenant, ſprinkled them with the ſoule of the beaſts; and the blood of the new Covenant is the blood of the ſoule of Chriſt, though not the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Cor. 11.27. <hi>He is guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 If by blood be meant the ſoul, how neceſſary is the cup? Chriſt gave not his fleſh, but blood alſo; how doe the Papiſts abuſe poor men in keeping it away?</p>
            <p n="2">2 If by the blood be meant in the Scripture the ſoul, multitudes of Scripture are not yet underſtood but in a carnal ſence, which wil ſpiritually in glory appear on their manifeſtation.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Pilats</hi> ſin, namely, in mixing mans blood with the blood of the beaſts which hee ſacrificed to Satan, aggravates the ſinne.</p>
            <p n="4">4 If the body comprehends the blood, or the blood be ſpoke of as of the body only, why are they thus diſtinguiſhed? in a word, it is to ſet forth the Lords death, who dyed in ſoul, as well as body.</p>
            <p>Job 2.4. <hi>All that a man hath will be give for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> his ſoule,</hi> ver. 6. <hi>He is in thy hand, but ſpare his ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this agrees with that of Chriſt, <hi>What ſhall a man give in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of his ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Acts 20.24. <hi>I account not my ſoule dear to my ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The regenerate part ſpeaks (the ſpirit) which was above the ſoul.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It ſpeaks its eſteem of his ſoule.</p>
            <p n="3">3 On what account it ſpeaks ſo, it would not ſpeak ſo upon any other occaſion whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Ezek. 18.20. <hi>The ſoule that ſinneth, it ſhall dye.</hi> Orig. 13 Tom. on John pag. 191.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The ſpirit dyed in <hi>Adam, in Adam all die,</hi> by that which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Original ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48357:14"/>2 The ſoule that lives by another life in the body, and is under the law Morall, the tranſgreſſions whereof were death; ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere is intended the Lords mediate puniſhing of man with death by the Magiſtrate, or elſe immediate by himſelfe.</p>
            <p>In V. 3. <hi>Ye ſhall not have occaſion any more to uſe this proverb, the Fathers have eate ſowre grapes, and the Childrens teeth are ſet on edge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 This proverb was true in the ſpirits death, by that ſin is called originall in <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 God ſaith it ſhould be ſo no more.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Now the next death is of the ſoule, to which in the after Scripture he only alludes, Ver. 4. <hi>All ſoules are mine, as the ſoule of the Father, ſo of the Son, the ſoule that ſinneth it ſhall dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 No ſoule by juſtice dyeth, but for breach of the moral Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>one, which is properly its by act, not imputation.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It is clear, each man hath a particular ſoul, as well as ſpirit or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ody, if any two bodies had one ſoule, it were the Father and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, which the word doth ſay are diſtinct.</p>
            <p n="6">6 If yee underſtand by death, eternal death only, then yee make void the Law of God.</p>
            <p n="7">7 There is a notable diſtinction uſed by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. Fornication is ſin unto the body of all other ſin; and <hi>James,</hi> ſin ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from luſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Pet. 1.24. <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, and all the glory of man as the flower of the graſſe, the graſſe withereth and the flower thereof falleth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The body is the fleſh, the graſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſoule, the flower and glory of man.</p>
            <p n="3">3 As the graſſe withereth, the flower falleth,</p>
            <p n="4">4 The end of the one and the other ſeem to differ, as they differ in themſelves, but fade and fall together.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The graſſe and flower are of one nature, and ſubject to change, though differing in their forme and beauty.</p>
            <p>Object. 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Commit the keeping of their ſoules to him in well doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence men are to commit their ſoules as well as ſpirits to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. The ſoule is committed to God in well doing, not in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (as the ſpirit is ſaid to be) before, not in death.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſoule is kept from the evil of ſin, the ſpirit from the evill of puniſhment; the one before death, the other after death, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48357:14"/>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>James</hi> 5.20. <hi>Shall ſave a ſoule from death.</hi> Which proves a beleevers ſoul dieth not, or is not ſubject to death.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The naturall mans ſpirit is already dead.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſalvation here is not temporall but eternall; not now, but hereafter.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That is, he ſaves the ſoule from hell, the ſecond death, from which Chriſt ſaves ſoule and body of beleevers.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That this is the mind of God is clear, for God ſaves not the elects ſoule from the temporall death, or ſleep of the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Nor is it deſired of, or beneficiall to them, for death is theirs, and death is to mee gaine, ſaith St. <hi>Paul:</hi> ſo that this doctrine of the ſoules ſleep is not condemned, if underſtood according to the mind of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Object. 3. <hi>James</hi> 2.26. <hi>As the body without the ſpirit is dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 This ſhews the dependance of the body, for its naturall life is on the ſpirit as well as ſoule, when Chriſt gave up the ſpirit he dyed.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This is true, if yee underſtand breath here by ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And that the ſoules dependance is on the ſpirit alſo for life, in the reall abſence whereof it dieth.</p>
            <p>Object. 4. Act. 20.10. <hi>Trouble not your ſelves, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, his ſoule is in him:</hi> whence it appears the bodies dependance is on the ſoule only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. He ſpeaks of the ſoule, becauſe he felt the ſoule, and while that was felt in him, his ſpirit was in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſoul is more diſcernable and materiall then the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3 As ſoon as the ſpirit leaves a man, the ſoule is no longer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable to be in a man.</p>
            <p>Object. 5. Rev. 21.8. <hi>The lake burns with fire and brimſtone, is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you ſay the ſpirit is dead, you ſay the ſoule after dyeth, then that of hell is the third death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> The death of the ſpirit, and the after death of ſoule and body, is but one death on the whole man.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond death is not of a part, but the whole man, the one before, the other after the day of Judgement.</p>
            <p n="3">3 As the widow woman 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6. ſo all men naturall are dead (in ſpirit) while they live (in body and ſoule) being partly dead, and partly alive, untill death hath put an end to body and ſoule, foregoing the reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Job. 33.30. <hi>He hath delivered my ſoule from death, that my life may praiſe him in the light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48357:15"/>1 Soule and life are diſtinct.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The deliverance of his ſoule was when God chap. 2. ſaid to Satan, he ſhould not meddle with his ſoule, and all the reſt was given into his hand what ever he had.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Satans deſire was to have his ſoule, <hi>Skin for skin, and all that a man hath will he give for his ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 See what a corrupting of the word it is to read here, <hi>life</hi> for <hi>ſoul,</hi> as one word, and in it, one thing for another.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whiles he was denied his ſoule, he was denyed his life, becauſe his ſoule was delivered from death in the continuance of his life.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How</hi> Job <hi>knew God had given all except this, and that Satan asked his ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Doubtleſſe by inſpiration, all Scripture is given thereby.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He wrote doubtleſſely his own life, and then he did it as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of God to doe it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Note, if by ſoule were meant the immortal part of man, Satan durſt never have asked it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To theſe diſtinctions of ſpirit, ſoul, body, life, breath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> laid down in the word, how have the eyes and hearts of the wiſe and learned of the world been ſhut up, concerning which as <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> yea, and let me ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> could not al the learning of the <hi>Academies</hi> find out this? no, but deſtroy it; men ſought it in <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato, &amp;c.</hi> where it was not, not in the word where it is, and by their corrupt principles came to meaſure the Truth of God, not meaſuring them by the truth, whoſe philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy compared with Gods is vaine Philoſophy: a poor man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his ſpirit quickened by God, and the eye of his underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding opened to underſtand the mind of God, may out of the word teach all the Philoſophers in the world, and ſwallow up their Philoſophy, as the ſun a ſmall ſtars light. Oh let the word, and its principles be ſtudied, and theſe vain ſtudies be laid aſide! I make bold to ſay the day &amp; time is coming it wil be ſo. The world knows not the worth and uſe of Gods word, that uſe thoſe beggarly rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and dunghils, the forms of all tropes, metaphors, ſyllogiſms are laid down therein, and to be learned thence, that were a way taken to teach men thence, would ſanctifie the ſpeech and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of youth, and not corrupt it and darken it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Eccleſ. 3.19. <hi>That which befalleth the ſons of men befalleth beaſts, even one thing befalleth them, as the one dieth ſo dieth the other, yea,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48357:15"/>they have all one <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> breath,</hi> ſo that <hi>Adam</hi> hath no preheminence above a beaſt.</p>
            <p>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. 20. <hi>All goe into one place, all are of the duſt, and turn to duſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems man and beaſt are equall, and no difference then by this Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. He here ſpeaks of the <hi>Adam</hi> that turns to duſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The breath or aire the beaſt and man injoy, for the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life in the world, is the ſame indeed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And as for their death, as one dieth, ſo dieth the other.</p>
            <p>Note he yet diſtinguiſheth them in this.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That though they dye alike, the body and ſoule of the beaſt, that never riſeth againe, as that of man doth, chap. 11.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He hath clearly diſtinguiſhed them ver. 21. in their ſpirits, who knoweth the ſpirit of man that aſcendeth to ſupernals, and the ſpirit of a beaſt that deſcendeth, becauſe from beneath to its bed of earth, as the ſpirit to God from whence it came.</p>
            <p n="3">3 God hath excellently diſtinguiſhed them in their firſt form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in their more excellent being then the other creatures, ſhining in reaſon, underſtanding, wiſdome, knowledge, ſpeech.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polyc. Lyſerus</hi> on the firſt of <hi>Geneſis</hi> gives this diſtinction between the ſoule of man and beaſt. <hi>Anima omnis carnis ſanguis ejus eſt, de ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis autem anima nuſpiam ita loquitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ill.</hi> The ſoule in the grave to the body, is as the life of the ſeed in the earth, which when the firſt body dieth, it riſeth up a new body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42.</p>
            <p>Object. 6. <hi>Since God breathed but one breath into</hi> Adam, <hi>he had but one life,</hi> Gen. 2.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1 Our tranſlation ſaies ſo, but corruptly, the Scripture in the Hebrew hath it in the plurall, lives, of different nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This appears, becauſe there are ſeverall deaths ſpoke of in the word, and fulfilled in man, one on his ſpirit, which differs in kind from that of the ſoule, and then there is death in hell; as God of one matter made many creatures, ſo of one breath many lives.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Adam was created mortall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Death entered by ſin into the world, and firſt ceized on his immortall part the ſpirit, and after on the ſoule, had not man finned, death had never been on ſoul or ſpirit.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:48357:16"/>
            <p>Object. 6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.20. <hi>This night they ſhall require thy ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems hence the ſoule is immortall, and was taken from the body by the devils. Note the words are parabolicall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Who theſe <hi>they</hi> are, is not ſet down in the Scripture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore going, or that that followeth after.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By <hi>they</hi> are meant the grave and death, of whom God ſaith, I will ranſome them from the hand of the grave, and power of death, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14. death hath the ſoule firſt, and after the grave hath ſoule and body.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That the grave requires ſuch a ſoule as fitted for it, and the manner, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.9. the <hi>grave</hi> from beneath is moved for thee, to meet thee at thy coming. And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.14. the grave opened her mouth wide. And <hi>Salomons</hi> Proverbs tel what ſhe means by her cry, <hi>give give</hi> me this or that ſoule, <hi>Job</hi> 17.1. the graves are ready for me.</p>
            <p n="4">4 As the grave, ſo death and the law, compare <hi>Pſ.</hi> 118.18. <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe are for death to death, God gives him up to death to take him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 7 <hi>He ſhould rather have ſpoke of his body then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> As the fool ſpake to his ſoule not body, ſo doth God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If the ſoule be required, the body muſt be.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ſoule and body lie in grave.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The foole had more wit then we, he ſaw his ſoul did partake of the meat he eat, and drink, and mirth in them; which I have not underſtood.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>In what was his folly then?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 In that he made proviſion for the fleſh not ſpirit, and took up his reſt in theſe earthly things, as if he needed no more.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In that he had goods for many years, and his ſoule might take its eaſe, and never thought his life was of ſo ſhort continuance.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That he was now to go to the grave, when theſe ſhould be left to he knew not whom, and he have no more to doe with any ſuch things.</p>
            <p>Object. 8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9.10. <hi>The ſoules under the Altar cry, how long before thou avenge our blood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hieron. ad Vigilantium Ep. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ais enim &amp;c. ſubter aram Dei animas Apoſtolorum &amp; martyrum conſediſſe, nec poſſe ſuis tumulis, neque ubi volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt eſſe preſentes in terra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. The way of anſwering <hi>Tropological</hi> ſayings hath been,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48357:16"/>
               <hi>Theologia ſymbolica non eſt argumentativa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 But to anſwer it indeed, is to know what the Altar is, and that is Chriſt, at whoſe feet the Martyrs, as the beaſts ſlaine, had their blood poured out, and to which here the Spirit alludes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Where the ſoules are that are ſaid to bee under the Altar? <hi>Reſp.</hi> Where ever they are, they are under the Altar, and not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of Chriſt; as Chriſts ſoule was not left of his Father; hence they are ſaid to ſleep in <hi>Jeſus: and the dead in Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13, 14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.52.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The ſoules are ſaid to cry after they were ſlain, <hi>ergo,</hi> not dead. <hi>Reſp.</hi> A ſoul hath no articulate voyce to cry with, and therefore can be nothing elſe, but Gods beholding the blood and paſt death, the enemy of Saints, Antichriſt, had cruelly ſpilt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Here are the ſoules, and blood of ſoules; the cry is from the ſoul, not the blood: <hi>Reſ.</hi> It was the ſame in <hi>Abels</hi> blood, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. the ſoul is not ſeen nor heard.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Of this Altar ſpeaks the Apoſtle, <hi>We have an Altar, which they that ſerve at the Tabernacle have no right to eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 As the Altar is a metaphoricall ſpeech, ſo the ſoules cry, and the ſouls being under the Altar, under which ſome Goſpel truth, is myſtically repreſented thereby unto us; as that the blood of Saints now came to be inquired after, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.24. and 19.2. and 16.6.</p>
            <p>Note from the nearneſſe of blood and the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.4, 5. God giving leave to man to eate fleſh, forbid him to eate blood before the Ceremoniall Law.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Under the Ceremoniall Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3 After the Ceremoniall Law in the Goſpel eſtate, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.29. by which the eſteem, and myſtery of Chriſts blood in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is exalted.</p>
            <p n="4">4 On this ground Marriages of ſuch as are of conſanguinity and next affinity with the Husband and Wife, are forbid, becauſe of confuſion.</p>
            <p n="5">5 There is in eating blood a confuſion of ſouls with ſoules, as <hi>Pilat</hi> mingled the blood of men with blood of beaſts.</p>
            <p>Obje. 9. <hi>Every creature of God is good, &amp;c. for it is ſanctified by the Word and prayer,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.4, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Note the dependance of its lawfulneſſe becauſe ſanctified by the word, but if the word forbid a thing, then it is otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Object. 10. <hi>Not that goeth into a man, but that which commeth out doth defile a man,</hi> Mat. 15.11.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:48357:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſ.</hi> This is ſpoken in contempt of a natural defilement by meat, eaten without waſht hands, as being the cauſe of Chriſts ſpeaking the words.</p>
            <p>Note under the Goſpell the eating blood is forbid, for the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to be had to the drinking of the blood of Chriſt Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, alſo.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. <hi>To the pure all things are pure.</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. <hi>Their Wife and children are pure, yet not to be eat, ſo blood is pure, but not to be eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. The Apoſtle ſhews it was a ſign of the falſe Teachers to command to abſtain from meates, calling it doctrine of devils, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.21.</p>
            <p n="1">1 See abſtinence was from meat, not from drinking blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It was on a religious ground, not a morall ground, as this.</p>
            <p n="3">3 There was an abſtinence from meat ſacrificed to Idols, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Object. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.25, 27. <hi>What ever is ſold in the Shambles, and what ever is ſet before you, eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> The Gentiles themſelves, but in their Temples and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, did abſtain from eating and drinking blood.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The abſtinence ſpok of to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> was Judaizing abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from meats.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That of <hi>Timothy</hi> was Antichriſts corrupt worſhip, and religion placed in ſuch things.</p>
            <p>Object. 11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28. <hi>Fear not thoſe that kill the body, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not kill the ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 This Scriptures obſcurity is to bee explained by <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.4. which was ſpoke at the ſame time, and the ſame thing intended in that of <hi>Luke,</hi> as that of <hi>Matthew,</hi> as in the verſes before theſe Scriptures, and after, they being the ſame words, matter and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in one, as in the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In which this general rule is to be obſerved, for the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the hiſtorians of Chriſts life.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That what ſeems to be obſcure in one, we are to ſeek an expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of in the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2 What ſeems wanting in one, wee ought to ſeek the ſupply thereof in the other.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That the mind of God is not fully knowne in one hiſtory, if the ſame be recorded by another, nay, nor in two, if recorded in three, as many are; Now this ſtory and words are only ſet down in this <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 12 in which two, yee have the mind of God concerning the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:48357:17"/>
            <p>Matth. 10.28. <hi>Fear not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule, but rather fear him that is able to deſtroy both ſoule and body in hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Luk. 12.4. <hi>Be not afraid of them that can kill the body, and after that have no more that they can doe; but I will forewarn you whom yee ſhall fear, fear him, which after he hath killed, hath power to caſt into hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Life is diſtinguiſhed, as I ſhewed you before, from the ſoul. which dyeth by the death of the body, but not in it, being diſtinct from it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Life as thus diſtinct from the ſoule, is ſaid to be taken away by the ſword, <hi>Job</hi> 33.18. <hi>He keepeth back his ſoul from the pit, and his life from periſhing by the ſword.</hi> Thus alſo in <hi>ver.</hi> 22. In which life which periſheth by the ſword, is that called here the killing of the body, for that is that man doth; on which diſſolving the chain of life, the Spirit leaves the ſoule; and the ſoule, ſay ſome, lyeth in the body aſleep in the grave, and under the Altar.</p>
            <p>Nor others it is dead by the ſpirits departure from the ſoule, as the body by lifes departure from it, in which is diſſolved the moſt glorious fabrick of the earth.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaks of that killing of the ſoul which is after death, and not at the diſſolution of the body in death, even of caſting the ſoul and body into hell.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Note on the killing of the body you have compleated the firſt death of ſpirit, ſoule and body in unbeleevers.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In that is to be done after, is the ſecond death, which men have no hand in, when God onely caſts ſoule, and ſpirit, and body into hel, which is the ſecond death; which is that Chriſts eie is upon,</p>
            <p n="3">3 Or that is after the death of the body to be done on it, is to raiſe the ſoule and awake that, quicken the body, reſtore the ſpirit, and then bring it to Judgement!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is appointed to all to dye, and after that to come to Judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note in this place clearly are expreſſed but two parts of man, his body, his ſoule, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſpirit being dead before.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Man, every man, undeniably conſiſts of three, ſoul, body &amp; ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ſpirit muſt be underſtood here as well as the reſt; and that in the ſoul which canot be killed nor dyeth, not in the way of man.</p>
            <p n="4">4 He ſpeaks of the ſoule rather then ſpirit, becauſe the men of the world are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in their very ſpirits; yea, God <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. ſays, man is fleſh: ſoule, ſpirit, body, are called fleſh in that place, through the carnall mind which was in them, eating, drinking, marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48357:18"/>building, planting, onely thought on.</p>
            <p>Note from the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth <hi>trucidare,</hi> to tear, rend, cut and ſlaſh, which may bee done by man on the body, or beaſts; but the ſoule men cannot come at to uſe it in like kind, being of a more ſpirituall ſubſtance and nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That Chriſts eye is eſpecially on this, to take away the diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts hung on the hearts of his people, ſeeing ſome whipt, others cut, ſtoned, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 25. ſawen aſunder, ſlain with the ſword, ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37. why this trucidation of men is but on the body, the ſoule they cannot make ſuffer in this kind, that joyes within whiles the body indures this without; they cannot tear that, if not that, much leſſe the ſpirit, <hi>Job</hi> 33.18, 20, 22, 28. the life the ſword deſtroys, not the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Heb. 6.19. <hi>Which hope we have as an anchor of the ſoule:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Acts 2.26. Having ſpoke that the <hi>heart ſhould be glad, and the tongue rejoyce,</hi> in which the ſoule was intimated, <hi>my fleſh alſo ſhall reſt in hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 It hopes as the ſoule, and with the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſoule and fleſh, though they goe to the grave together, yet hope in the Word, Truth, Power and Promiſes of God, it ſhall ariſe and be incorruptible, though it ſee it not.</p>
            <p n="3">3 This is ſignificantly manifeſted in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> moreover (that is, beſides my ſoule) <hi>my fleſh ſhall reſt in hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 In that hope is the ſouls, and the only uſe of it when the ſoule and body lye in the grave, it deſcribes the ſoules nature, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
            <p>The Metaphor is thus opened.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Whiles the ſpirituall man in ſpirit, ſoule, and body was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through the ſea of this world by the gales of the Spirit of God, and helpe of the north ſtar, and the Word its compaſſe ſteered its courſe towards heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2 But when the Spirit, the Pilot left the ſhip, the body, the ſoul went no f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rther, but made uſe of hope as its Anchor, and there reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where the Spirit left it.</p>
            <p n="3">3 W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere it waited for the return of the Spirit from the Lord, and the Lord, bringing it to the deſired port and Haven of reſt with the Lord, in heavenly places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heraclitus</hi> ſaid, <hi>Animis mors eſt aquam fieri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:48357:18"/>1 The Naturaliſts ſay, the water that came out of Chriſts ſide was that was contained in the Pericardian.</p>
            <p n="2">2 What relation this had to the ſoule, or the ſoule to it, I dare not determine.</p>
            <p n="3">3 This we know, that the Sacraments of Baptiſme was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with water, the Lords Supper with blood. <hi>Auguſt. Sacramenta manant e latere Chriſti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clemens. Alex. paed. liq.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sanguis enim invenitur primum genitus in homine, quem nonnulli auſi ſunt dicere ſubſtantiam animae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auſtins</hi> wrote 16 chap. to prove the immortality of the ſoule, in all which I remember not; he makes uſe of one Text of Scripture, but Philoſophically handles the Queſtion; nor doth he mention the ſpirit; ſuch a darkneſs in his time Philoſophy had drawn on men who, ſeeking to be wiſe became fools.</p>
            <p>Ezek. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6 9. <hi>I ſaid unto thee when thou waſt in thy blood live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 A naturall man in that eſtate is as a child at his birth, in blood and corruption, as he came out of the womb.</p>
            <p n="2">2 God in his blood-eſtate ſaid live, that is quickned her by his Word and Spirit: Thrice <hi>live,</hi> firſt in ſoule, then ſpirit, naturally, then ſpiritually.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. God in love covers her nakedneſſe, makes a Covenant, and becomes her Husband.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9. Hee waſhed her with water baptiſme, and waſhed away her blood, and anoynted her with oyle, that is, with the Holy Spirits Baptiſme after beleeving and baptiſme, which ſhewes in this place Gods eye in eſpeciall was on the eſtate of the Goſpell Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. A Crown on her head, the ſtate of the Goſpel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14. Her renown went among the Gentiles, when follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Gentiles call.</p>
            <p>Note ſhe was alive yet in her blood, when God ſays again and again live, and ſhews her life was nothing which ſhe had in her blood. I might on this ſubject exceed, were it to the purpoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> In the caſting forth of ſeed was thy ſoule, where is the male, in coition with the female. <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. He is in his blood in the womb, when God firſt gave life to him, as to <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:48357:19"/>
            <p>Blood is the ſeat of the Soule, and ſo related to, and concerned in it, that great are the myſteries of it, as concerning Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>THe new Teſtament was made in the blood of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Without ſhedding of blood is no remiſſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The blood of Jeſus cleanſeth the conſcience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. and from all ſin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19, 20. By his blood we have an admiſſion to God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22. Water is for the body baptiſm; blood, the conſcience.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The uſe whereof was ſet out in ſprinkling pots and cups, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.2. this ſpeaks peace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.13.</p>
            <p>Note in this was the glorious act of redemption wrought and juſtice more excellently ſatisfied then in what was done on the body.</p>
            <p n="1">1 God requiring blood for blood, when a man was to dye for ſtaying of a man; ſo now, man being for ſin to dye, he cannot be ſaved, but by the death of his Son for Man.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He requires ſoule for ſoule, which are indeed the ſame, and without this there is no remiſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ap.</hi> the neceſſity of this knowledge I commend to all to judge of, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10.24. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.5, 6. <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.23. typified in the beaſts ſlaine for ſacrifice <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.21. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Three beare witneſſe in heaven in the God-head, the Father, the Word, the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Three bear witneſſe in earth, in the manhood of Chriſt, the Spirit, the Water, the Blood.</p>
            <p>Now theſe three accordingly are applied by Chriſt to man, for and towards his reſtauration deſcending to him, in which as <hi>Eliah,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.34. Chriſt applyed himſelfe to man to reſtore him.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Uſing his Spirit to quicken the dead ſpirit of man, by which the Lord is called <hi>a quickening Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 After that hee applyes the water, anſwering to his humane nature, to waſh the body by baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The blood in the Lords Supper, and in redemption by his blood, which is the ſoule part of Chriſt, to cleanſe the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>John</hi> 19.34, 35.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48357:19"/>1 If we have not the uſe of Chriſt in theſe ſeverall ways as he hath appointed to communicate himſelfe to man, our faith is vain.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This of the ſpirit is all that, and the firſt only neceſſary thing to be apprehended, for the fleſh profiteth nothing, it is the ſpirit quickeneth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.63.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The end of grace here is, that men may be raiſed in ſpirit, and be partaker of the firſt reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. unleſſe this be done, Chriſt doth nothing, and this is to be done on the dead ſpirit, or there is nothing done.</p>
            <p n="4">4 As the ſpirit hath its good by Chriſts Spirit, ſo the ſoule by Chriſts ſoule, and fleſh by Chriſts fleſh.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The good of each was properly to ariſe from the ſeverall parts of Chriſt to thoſe in man, as the ſinner needed them; Chriſt being proportioned, and fitted to be a perfect Saviour.</p>
            <p>Object. Gen. 35, 18. <hi>As her ſoul was going forth, (for ſhe died. The ſoul) as the ſpirit goeth forth of the body at death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. The diſſolution of that unity was between ſpirit and ſoule, and ſoule and body, as the cauſe of death.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is like the ſoule goeth forth with the ſpirit, though it is not ſaid to goe to God, but dyeth; or ſleeps, as with the ſoule fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows after the life, and the body dyeth.</p>
            <p>Object: <hi>The ſoule and the ſpirit are one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, that is againſt Scripture.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>As the ſpirit goeth forth to God, ſo the ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> The Scriptures ſay not ſuch a word of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the new Teſtament ſo often uſed hath a notable ſignificancy in it, to ſet this out; for it ſignifies man the whole at death, to ſuffer a reſolution of parts; the Spirit divided from Soule, and Soule from Body in the corrupting thereof.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48357:20"/>
               <head>That the Soule ſuffers not hell Torments untill the laſt Judgement.</head>
               <p>ROm. 2.8. ſpeaks of the day of wrath, which the ſoule that is impenitent treaſures up wrath by rejecting Gods Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</p>
               <p n="2">2 This day is called the day of the revelation of the righteous Judgement of God, which muſt be underſtood the laſt and great day of Judgement, when, and not before, the judgement of God is revealed.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. Then <hi>every one ſhall receive according to their works.</hi> Ver. 7. <hi>When our mortality ſhall put on immortality,</hi> and not before.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Ver.</hi> 9. Then, and not before, ſhall be tribulation and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh on every ſoule of man that doth evill, the Jew firſt, and then the Gentile.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wiſdom</hi> 3.1, 6. By ſo much authority as it hath being Apocryphal proves it; which whiles it agrees with the word, I prefer before any authority that is meer humane.</p>
               <p>Under the old Teſtament theſe were ſet forth diſtinct in Chriſt, and ſo in us.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The Goat was ſlain and ſacrificed, the body.</p>
               <p n="2">2 His blood poured out, the ſoule.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The ſcape-Goat went away into the wilderneſſe, the ſpirit, which is not under the power of man.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>This Goat is meant the divine Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. They were two Goats, of the ſame nature, and did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſame perſon of the humanity; only part, as the body and ſoule dyed; part was beyond the power of man and death.</p>
               <p n="2">2 How unpoſſible the divine glory of the Divine nature of the Lord Jeſus could admit of any ſhadow of change, as to bee ſet out dividedly under the repreſentation of a Goat, the note of repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, I leave all to judge.</p>
               <p>To reconcile the ſeeming differences, it is firſt neceſſary they be ſtated and compared.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Part of the difference is about the place, or <hi>ubi</hi> where they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48357:20"/>are, which are ſet downe in Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">1 To be in the grave.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To be under the Altar.</p>
               <p n="3">3 To be in the body.</p>
               <p n="4">4 To be in heaven.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Note the firſt two are thus reconciled; thoſe that die the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death of all, and are interred, their ſoules are in grave.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Thoſe whoſe blood (as that of the ſlain beaſts) was for Chriſt poured out at the feet of the altar, and had no grave for their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, nor burial, their ſoules are under the altar, and not as others; the manner of their ſouls preſence with Chriſt is a cry againſt thoſe that ſhed their blood, in which the ſoul &amp; blood are diſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p n="3">3 As <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2. Whether in the body or out of the body I cannot tell, yet by what is ſaid <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.18. it goeth out of the body when it hovers over it, and lieth down with it in the grave, or after enters into it, when dead, and ſleeps in it; the ſpirit and life departed from it not being willing to be alone, may return to the body as before; it not vaniſhing, as the life; nor going to God as the ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="4">4 No Scripture ſays that any ſoule is yet in heaven: <hi>Chriſt is the firſt fruits of them that ſleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second part of the difference is between theſe Scriptures, ſay,</p>
               <p n="1">1 That the ſouls dye.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That they only ſleep.</p>
               <p>Note, In this is the great controverſie; for by the one it is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and the other it ſeems not to be ſo.</p>
               <p n="1">1 For reconciliation we are to diſtinguiſh between the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nature of Death in theſe parts of man; for as the parts differ in themſelves, ſo their deaths differ; the ſpirit is dead while in the body, and the ſoule and body alive, but never ſuffers corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the body doth in its death, whoſe death is a totall priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, ſence, and motion, ending in corruption.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſoules death differs from that of the ſpirit, and that of body.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Gods leaving the ſpirit, it dies by withdrawing the ſpirits operation from it, which when by Chriſt it returned into man, he is raiſed from the ſpirit death.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſoule leaving the body, it dyes.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:48357:21"/>3 The ſpirit leaving the ſoule, it ſuffers its death; as the body lives by the ſoule, ſo the ſoule by the ſpirit; ſo that when the ſpirit is gone, the ſoule is dead; as the body moves not without the ſoule, ſo the ſoule acts not without the ſpirit be in her, who is its life, in its as well natural as ſpiritual being.</p>
               <p>Concluſion,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Unbeleevers, and all men by nature are ſubject to this death of ſoul, as that of ſpirit and body, as being the way and means de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned of God for their diſſolution.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Beleevers now, though their ſpirits forſake the ſoule, yet the ſpirit of Chriſt being with their ſoules, and they ſaid to ſleepe in Jeſus, it is a ſleepe to them, though a death to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As <hi>ſomnum</hi> is <hi>imago mortis,</hi> it ſhews the difference ſeems not much between theſe, there is at leaſt the image of the one in the other, though not the other.</p>
               <p n="4">4 This is a further clearing of the preciouſneſs of the firſt reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and Chriſts ſo oft ſaying to his people, they ſhould not ſee death, nor taſte of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> To ſhew what a ſweet uſe of Chriſt in mans forſaken condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is loſt and unknown. Now if Chriſt bee with us, and wee in Chriſt, though in the grave, what matters it? we are ſafe enough, whiles in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The death of the ſoule is, that it is not with God, nor God with it, in the abſence of its ſpirit, its naturall life and body; but ſin and death hath dominion over them, which it hath not over thoſe aſleep in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Chriſts ſoule is ſaid to dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Chriſts ſoule was left of its ſpirit, as ours, which was one part of this death.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hee cries out, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> which was that other part; God forſook the creature, the ſoule in Chriſt, of which, O how ſenſible was hee, though wee are not of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits death.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This is more clear, <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoule in grave,</hi> that is, no longer but the appointed time of three dayes, and after God and his ſpirit would come to the ſoule, and alſo raiſe the body.</p>
               <p n="4">4 This was he in ſoul to ſuffer with man, that he might become
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48357:21"/>a ranſome for, and redeem men from death and the grave, where hee indured what man by ſinne ſhould ſuffer, under death in the grave.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hence thoſe that beleeve not, and are not in Jeſus, doe not ſleep in Jeſus, but are dead; and ſo only are ye to underſtand the Scriptures, when it ſpeaks of the dead in ſoul and body, it cals them dead only; but of the beleevers as of men that ſleep, and ſleep in Chriſtin the ſoule.</p>
               <p n="6">6 When as the Scriptures ſpeak of the dead in Chriſt, then they cheifly reſpect the bodies, not the ſoules of Saints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> Shews what multitudes of lyes and errors are taught in the name of Chriſt, and how deſtructive the doctrine now taught is.</p>
               <p n="2">2 How obſcure the faith of Chriſt and the Goſpel is in this, and multitudes of other caſes, is not ſeen nor credited.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Confirmation of this is deduced hence, The ſpirit dieth, and the body dyeth, and by the argument of the ſouls mortality; that though God hath ſaid in many Scriptures, the <hi>ſoul doth dye,</hi> and <hi>the ſoule that ſinneth ſhall dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>The wages of ſin is death, and the ſoul that ſinneth ſhall dye;</hi> and yet it muſt not dye, how contrary this is to Gods word, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and mans deſert, let the world be judge.</p>
               <p n="5">5 It is ſet down in the future tence, <hi>ſhall die,</hi> and ſhews that it is to be another death on the ſoule, then what was on man by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> fall.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>They make the ſoul doth dye, but it is in Hell hereafter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> That death of ſoule is a death in which ſpirit and body doth partake with it, and is after the reſurrection, as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1 But that death is called the ſecond death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In that it is called the ſecond death, and ſoule, body, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are to die, therein it is cleare all theſe muſt firſt ſuffer a firſt death, before this ſecond, which by the now doctrine the ſoule doth not.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14, 16. In one the ſoules are ſaid to <hi>ſleep in Jeſus,</hi> in the other, the body <hi>dead in Jeſus,</hi> the ſame perſons being ſpoken of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:48357:22"/>
               <head>Reaſons why the Soules of Saints ſleep, but of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeleevers are dead.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, The beleeving ſoule through the ſeed of faith and hope, ſleeps only, and is not dead as thoſe without hope.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The ſoule though it be left of its own ſpirit, yet it is in the ſpirit of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In this is fulfilled, that the beleever <hi>ſeeth not, nor doth hee taſt of death,</hi> he being by his faith, in the name of the Son of God, <hi>kept from the power of death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Chriſt hath by his ſouls death, redeemed theirs from that death, the ſouls of unbeleevers dye.</p>
               <p n="1">1 This is in <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſet forth, <hi>John</hi> 11.4. <hi>This ſickneſſe is not to death,</hi> his ſoul not dying. <hi>Ver.</hi> 11. <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth,</hi> they not underſtanding the ſoules ſleep. <hi>Ver.</hi> 14. he ſpake more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>he is dead,</hi> ſpeaking of his body. <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. if not thus under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, is a myſtery, that <hi>the ſickneſſe was not to death,</hi> and yet hee <hi>dyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 This is ſeen in <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> 7.59. Hee commends his ſpirit to Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 60. his ſoule is made aſleep, his body chap. 8.2. is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the grave, the ſignificancy of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for his death, chap. 8.1 is exceeding great, and ſignifies his reſolution; as the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king down of a houſe.</p>
               <p>The life of the ſoule is maintained within it by hope, and differenceth the dead and living ſoules.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Hence hope is ſaid to be the anchor of the ſoule, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Apoſtles 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13. <hi>I would not have you ignorant Brethren concerning thoſe that ſleep, that they mourn not as</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>thoſe others,</hi> thoſe that have no hope.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Mark.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Why lament yee and weep? the child is not dead but ſleepeth,</hi> In <hi>Ver.</hi> 35. the Text ſaith, <hi>ſhe is dead.</hi> And <hi>Ver.</hi> 40. They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided Chriſt for ſaying, <hi>ſhe was not dead but ſlept;</hi> may they ſay, doe yee call this a ſleep? it is a deadly one: know yee no better when a man ſleeps, from when he is dead? for which they were ſhut out, and not ſuffered to ſee the ſalvation of God.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Chriſt he ſpeaks here of their ſorrow and howling.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Of her ſoules eſtate, not bodies, and that they had no cauſe to lament thus for her, ſhee was not of the number of dead ſoules
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48357:22"/>that dyed without hope, but of the living ſoules that ſleep by Jeſus.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That this is the mind of the ſpirit in this place <hi>ver.</hi> 41. he ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſhews ſhe was in body dead, and was raiſed by the Lord Jeſus, not only from the place ſhe lay down on, but from the dead.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14, 16. Doe ſet forth a diſtinction as in the body and ſoul, ſo in Chriſts vertue extended to them.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The ſouls are ſaid to ſleep, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>per Jeſum,</hi> by or through Jeſus, if it were not for Jeſus they would be as the reſt, not aſleep but dead; where now they are not dead, but ſleep.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The bodies they are dead <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in Chriſt;</hi> Jeſus is applyed to the ſoules ſalvation, and Chriſt to the body; though elſewhere this diſtinction is not uſed, but 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.16. If the dead are not raiſed, Chriſt is not raiſed, <hi>Ver.</hi> 18. thoſe that fleep in Chriſt are deſtroyed here: the ſleepers, or ſouls are ſaid to ſleep in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> The Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. Saith by Chriſt ſetting out the efficient and meritorious cauſe of mans ſleep to be Jeſus, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered it from its death, and gave it ſleep.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſoule may be ſaid, as well as body, to ſleep in Chriſt, by the power of Jeſus ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This here of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.18. is a ſuppoſition.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Shewing that if they ſlept in Chriſt, and roſe not, they ſlept not by Jeſus, they had not effectually ſalvation by him.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſoule and body were deſtroyed.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The dead and ſleepers are diſtinguiſhed in the 16 and 18. verſes.</p>
               <p>Note only in the Epiſtle of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> he ſpeakes to men beleeving, and aſſenting; in this of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to men doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, queſtioning, contradicting, which is the ground of that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſeems to be in his ſpeech.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20.</p>
               <p>Note by this only that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20. is moſt ſignificantly open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, where it is ſaid, <hi>Chriſt is the firſt fruits of them that ſleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is, Chriſt in his ſoule was the firſt was raiſed from ſleep, and entered into heaven, and aſcended to his Father with his dead body made alive.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Where the controverſie of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> going to Heaven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts reſurrection is to be allowed of without queſtioning
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48357:23"/>this Scripture-Truth; for it was of thoſe that ſleepe, Chriſt was the firſt fruits; he ſaith not of others, that ſlept not, as <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> did not.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That this muſt be the ſoule, not the ſpirit, for that goeth to God immediately, of all Saints.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Nor of the body, that is dead in the grave: nor is he ſaid to be the firſt fruits of the dead, becauſe the ſouls, not the bodys eſtate diſtinguiſheth the Saints from unbeleevers; in themſelves the one is as wel dead, rots and corrupts, as the other, but the ſoul of one ſleeps, the other is dead.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>The ſoule while in the body is called the ſouls, but when it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts it is called the ſpirit, becauſe diſtinct from the body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> The ſoule is called the ſoule after death, as well as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſpirit is called the ſpirit in the body, and out of it, when joyned to the ſoule and body.</p>
               <p n="3">3 It is not one thing in the body, and another out of it.</p>
               <p>And here I cannot paſſe by a myſtery not yet clear to the world, in expreſſing the word for the dead in the plurall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Sometimes as alluding to mankind, among which Chriſt lay, and from among whom Chriſt was raiſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Othertimes, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. being declared to be the ſon of God in power, according to the ſpirit of ſanctification, through the reſurrection of the <hi>deads;</hi> that is, his dead body and dead ſoule.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>The dead ſate up,</hi> ſpeaking only of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that part ſate up, and therefore expreſſed in the ſingular num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
               <p n="4">4 When Chriſt is ſaid to riſe from the dead in the plural (or any other) I underſtand their ſoules riſing from dead ſoules, with whom their ſouls were, being in their ſtate as of one of them. And I underſtand their bodies riſing from dead bodys with whom they were as one of them during their eſtate of death.</p>
               <p n="5">5 This I take thus to be cleared, man conſiſts of ſpirit, ſoule, and body, who have differing lives ſubject to differing deaths, from which deaths man by Chriſt comes to be redeemed in differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ways, by differing means.</p>
               <p n="6">6 In our tranſlations <hi>deads</hi> ſhould be put for <hi>dead,</hi> when expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the plurall, and in the ſingular, when by the ſpirit ſet downe ſo in the originall.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:48357:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Application of this point of the blood of Chriſt,</hi> as it concerns the Soul of Chriſt, it is of admirable uſe and concernment to us.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>General. As Chriſt communicates his Spirit, ſo his Body,</hi> Matth. 26.26. Mark 14.22. Luke 22.19.</p>
               <p n="1">1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. The Bread that we break, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. Unbelievers diſcerned not the Lords Body in the Bread, and it was the ſin of the <hi>Capernaits,</hi> that cry out, <hi>How can this man give us of his fleſh to eat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. For not diſcerning the Lords Body, they were guilty that did partake of the Sacrament of the afflictings and tormentings the Jews put him to, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The neceſſity of its being received (when in the way of God) becauſe the Lord enjoyned it to be done in remembrance of him: And farther, <hi>John</hi> 6.53. <hi>If ye eat not the fleſh, and drink not the blood of the Son of Man, ye have no life in you,</hi> vid. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 54,55.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note.</hi> The fleſh is communicated to our fleſh as fleſh, as his Spirit to our ſpirit; but the fleſh, without the ſpirit, profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; or the Spirit quickneth the dead ſpirit, and the fleſh feedeth thoſe made alive, when living, not before.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>General. Chriſt having a Spirit and Body, communicates them, and ſhews the neceſsity of our partaking of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quaere.</hi> Whether Chriſt having a Soule, it be not as neceſſary we be partakers of that, as of the other parts of Chriſt, if we expect Salvation by him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether the ſoul be not communicated in the blood of Chriſt, or whether there be any other way of communion of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether our communion of the blood of Chriſt be not of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable price, uſe and comfort to us, and to be remembred of us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether his ſoul was not poured out to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath, as well as body crucified and broken.</p>
               <p>The third part of man is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the body <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the fleſh, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Adam</hi> reſpects the matter <hi>éx qua,</hi> as it was in its form, as fitted
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48357:24"/>for the Spirit and ſoule its informing forme.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Ephar</hi> reſpects the matter <hi>ex qua,</hi> out of which God at firſt took the <hi>Adam,</hi> and gave it its form.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Baſar</hi> reſpects the body of man abſtractively from ſoule and ſpirit, as it was after it became a living ſoule, every part being fleſh.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Sooma</hi> is ſpoken of relatively, as it is the Tabernacle of the ſoule, and ſpirit, having compleatly in it all the members that make up a perfect man in the bodily part.</p>
               <p n="1">1 This <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> lives, who was made of duſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It is ſaid <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which words I thus read, <hi>and there was to the ſoule of</hi> Adam <hi>life,</hi> ſo as that the ſoul was of the <hi>Adam,</hi> the earth.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This fleſh is contrary to the ſpirit, between which the ſoule is placed, who reſpects the fleſh in its inferiour parts, and the Spirit in its ſuperiour.</p>
               <p>Theſe two are contrary.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The fleſh maintains a war with the regenerate ſoule, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The fleſhly eſtate is ſuch, men cannot therein pleaſe God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.6, 7. the wiſdom thereof is death, and is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the Kingdome.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Man owes nothing to the fleſh, to live thereto, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.12.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.5. Maſters are ſaid to be Maſters according to the fleſh. In which was fignified</p>
               <p>Firſt, That their dominion was onely over the fleſh to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it, and on diſobedience, to puniſh them in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Secondly, As the Magiſtrate called the higher power, had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over the ſoule of man.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The Spirit that was onely under the Lord, in which ſence it is, that he that is called to be a Servant, is the Lords Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that is, in his ſpirit eſtate, for if <hi>the Son hath made you free, then are you free indeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note by which 1. No man is naturally free.</p>
               <p n="2">2 No man by any means can make himſelf free to any ſpirituall good.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The beſt man is made free by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The freedome from Chriſt is that freedome indeed, in which the dominion of Satan is deſtroyed.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:48357:24"/>3 There is a freedome which is not a freedome indeed, as in carnal, natural, ordinary things, when the ſoule is ſo in bondage to Satan, that it cannot have leave to reſtraine it from evil, or to act any good.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The natural ſervice or bondage of the fleſh was firſt inflicted on <hi>Cham</hi> by his fathers ſentence, for mocking of him in his nakedneſſe after wine.</p>
               <p n="5">5 His curſe was, he ſhould be <hi>a Servant of Servants,</hi> ſerving ſuch as ſerved Satan, and ſin in the luſts of the fleſh, which was indeed to be a drudge to the De vill manifeſted in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Note this, that fleſh is of the fleſh, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.</p>
               <p n="1">1 It withers and dyes, and is thence called mortall fleſh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11. yet <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.29. no man hateth his owne fleſh.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Being dead it reſolves againe into its firſt matter, which is duſt, and differs herein from the death of ſoule and ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="3">3 It corrupts alive and dead, and is very noyſom to its ſelf, and others, to ſee or ſmell of.</p>
               <p n="4">4 It ſhewes their vanity that glory after the fleſh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18.</p>
               <p>Note <hi>John</hi> 1.14.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>The word was made,</hi> or became, <hi>fleſh, Heb:</hi> 2.14. of <hi>the ſeed of</hi> David <hi>according to the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 In this fleſh God manifeſted himſelfe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In the body conſiſting of Bones, Nerves, Sinewes, cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the fleſh, called the body of his fleſh, <hi>He hath reconciled us by death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 The time of Chriſts being here with men, are called the days of his fleſh, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The Jewiſh Antichriſt was he that denyed Chriſt come in the fleſh, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.2. The Gentile Antichriſt took the authority and place of Chriſt to himſelfe, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. the Jewiſh Antichriſt is indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p n="6">6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. We have known Chriſt after the fleſh, hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth know we him no more.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.20. The fleſh is called the vaile of Chriſt, by which the God-head and glory of Chriſt came to be ſhadowed from the eyes of thoſe unbeleeving mortals the Lord had to doe with, whiles he was among men here below.</p>
               <p n="8">8 By which he is ſaid to prepare a new and living way for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48357:25"/>man to God; men before coming to God by <hi>Aaron,</hi> and bringing Beaſts, and Fruits, and Fowle not appearing before God empty, which God on the Sons aſſuming fleſh <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.8, 9. rejected &amp; now the new way (becauſe the other waxed old, and was done away,) took place; no man more with the ſacrifice of beaſts being to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before God, but the body God had prepared; Chriſt to be a Sacrifice for us, to which the Apoſtle alludes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.8: the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the holy ſignifying this, that as yet the way of the Holies was not made manifeſt, whiles, the firſt Tabernacle was ſtanding.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Chriſt was put to death in the fleſh, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>and</hi> 4.1.</p>
               <p>Note the fleſh, though it is the meaner and baſer part of man, yet it had means applyed to it of God for ſanctification, and is ſaid to be the Temple of the Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In the Lords taking our fleſh, in which it was exalted above the nature of Angels, it being aſſumed to the divine nature of God, God and Man making one Saviour.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Among the Ordinances under the Law, was circumciſion of the fleſh.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The Law of the Ten Commandements was a fleſhly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, though of a ſpiritual nature, it being to judge the fleſh by, and direct the body.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The blood of Buls and Goats that waſhed away the filth of the fleſh, which I take not to reſpect the outward uncleanneſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by any natural pollution, but ſoule-pollution: for all pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution is comprehended under filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, which I take thus to be done.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That there being ſin committed, by which pollution was contracted, the ſoule could not draw near to God without ſome flaine beaſt, for an offering, by which the fleſh was ſaid to be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and preſerved from that filth brought death corporal.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Spirit ſhews it was the blood of Chriſt offered up by the eternal Spirit to God, cleanſed the Conſcience from ſins, preſenting it blameleſs to God, which the other offerings could not do; by the other, they came to God, but not as by this.</p>
               <p>Now under the Goſpell, Baptiſme is an Ordinance ſaid to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed theſe 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. where to baptize, is a type, and now ſaveth us, being not the putting away of the ſpot of the fleſh; but the Anſwer of a good Conſcience to God by the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Yet the fleſh of Chriſt profits nothing, thoſe to whom the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48357:25"/>Spirit of Chriſt is not given, ſo that all mankind who have not his Spirit, have no profit by his fleſh, becauſe it is the Spirit muſt teach the fleſh to profit by Chriſt, or he gains nothing by it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vid. Aug. Lib. Quaeſt. Cap.</hi> 67. <hi>Anſelm</hi> on the words, <hi>Gregor. Mor. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 30. <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19. The <hi>expectation of the creature</hi> (that is, mans body, as in <hi>Phi.</hi> 1.20.) from without <hi>waiteth for the revelation of the Sons of God,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3 2. It being not untill then glorified, but corrupt.</p>
               <p>Ver. 20. <hi>The creature</hi> (man) <hi>is ſubjected to vanity, it not having</hi> (ought) <hi>but through him that hath ſubjected it in hope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ver. 21. <hi>For the creature it ſelfe</hi> (by which is ſtrictly taken the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) <hi>being made after the form of the other creatures</hi> (in the creation, from which the ſpirit and ſoule differed) <hi>ſhall be made free from the bondage of corruption</hi> (when at the laſt day it ſhal have put on incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <hi>into the liberty of glory</hi> (God being to be ſeen with theſe eyes, that now cannot ſee God and live) <hi>of the Sons of Gad in the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ver. 22. <hi>For we know that all</hi> (or the whole, <hi>creature</hi>) man, in his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſoule and body) he before having ſpoken of the ſoule diſtinct, in the hope, and the body in its vanity, nowſpeaks of all) <hi>groan together, and travel in pain together untill now:</hi> That is, the body labours under the wants of the ſoule; the ſoule, of the body; the ſpirit is burthened with the temptations of both, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>until now,</hi> that is, none as yet being poſſeſſed of this felicity.</p>
               <p>Ver. 23. And not only (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the body) but they, the ſpirit and ſoule) having the beginning of the ſpirit (his ſpirit quickening our ſpirit, that it cannot ſee death, but is partaker of the firſt reſurrection, and the ſoule ſupported by hope, ſleeping in Chriſt is free from corruption, far differing in its eſtate from that of the body; and thence after, <hi>we our ſelves</hi> is oppoſed to the body altogether, before ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We our ſelves, in our ſelves groan, looking out to the felicity, the redemption of our bodies.</hi> Here the revelation of ſons is reſerved to the laſt day, when beleevers ſhall be ſeparated from unbeleevers.</p>
               <p>Ver. 24. <hi>For by hope we are ſaved,</hi> in which he alludes to the look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, and expectation of the creature, ver. 19, 20, 23 and ſhews man is this creature, as being the only adequate object of hope.</p>
               <p>Ver. 25. Who onely by patience wait for the manifeſtation hereof upon the perſwaſions of the ſpirit aſſuring man hereof by the Word of God.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:48357:26"/>
               <p>Note verſe 23. Not onely <hi>the creature</hi> (the creature is added in Tranſlation,) ſignifying the body diſtinct from the ſoule and ſpirit; or the natural man of the firſt creation, from the ſpiritual of the regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as after.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Go out into all the world, preach the Goſpell to every creature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the ſoule, body, and ſpirit is the key of Scripture, and this hid, the myſterie of ſalvation is many waies hid; but eſpecially the way of teaching it, appears in this truth.</p>
               <p n="1">1 How men corrupt the ſence of the Word, and looſe the mind of God, for here they read every creature, and therefore St. <hi>Francis</hi> goeth and preacheth to the fiſhes, and why we on this command ſhould not preach to the beaſts and fowles, I know not.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Others there are, that ſay the Goſpel is to be preached to every, &amp;c. and therefore remiſſion of ſins and ſalvation of Chriſt is to be applyed to all the men on earth.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Say they, Chriſt redeemed all.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Word commands the Goſpel to be preached and applied to all.</p>
               <p>Note the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> uſually tranſlated <hi>omnis, every,</hi> as reſpecting the number of things, but when it admits not number, it is read <hi>all,</hi> as in the ſame ver. and <hi>Col.</hi> 1.6. for ye cannot ſay in every world, there being but one in all.</p>
               <p>N. Now ſo here, teach the Goſpel to every creature, why, no creature is capable of the teaching of the Goſpel, but man; and therefore God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned the teaching of none but him; if he did, as men read he did, then we that teach do not well to neglect them.</p>
               <p>N. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> I rather therefore tranſlate <hi>all the creature,</hi> as before <hi>all the world,</hi> and then ſhews,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the whole man hath ſweet mercies ſet out in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Goſpell is to be diſtributed to its ſeverall parts by the wiſe workman, to make him perfect.</p>
               <p n="1">1 There is Goſpel to reform the body, and form it to Chriſt, with moſt ſweet promiſes of its reſurrection and glory.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſoule, the Goſpel hath multitude of precious balmes for its wounds, and inſtructions how to take heed of the fleſh, to leave the world, to enjoy Chriſt, and what the Lord is, and will bee to the ſoule.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The Word divides between ſoule and ſpirit, and reproves the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48357:26"/>of that, and reformes it to the glorious image of the Sons of God.</p>
               <p>The Doctors Miniſtery was the firſt of theſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 3. for as yet they were not fitted to embrace the more ſpiritual knowledge of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, nor were they reformed in their loweſt part.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſoule, the Paſtors, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Peter</hi> was Paſtor in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems</hi> Church, and he faith yee are returned <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, unto the Paſtor that was an Office as miniſtring, and the Biſhop that was, he was a Ruling Officer, who was to reforme the affections and mind by exhortations, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19, 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>God having quickened the ſpirit, he by rules,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Teaches the ſpirit as it is able to hear and know God, and bear his yoake; which firſt is concerned in the reforming the outward man, or fleſh, and the ſoule in the lower parts thereof.</p>
               <p>In the miniſtery of the Teacher, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. Repentance, Baptiſm, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and Judgement concerning the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1, 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In the inſtructing of the ſoule in its more excellent part of the mind, affections, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22. and 15.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 11. fleſhly luſts fight againſt the ſoul, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Paſtor is of the ſoule, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In the inſtructing of the Spirit, which is the Evangeliſts work of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Under which three the Beleever is to bee perfected, in the firſt, hee is as a Babe, in the other as a Youth, in the laſt as a ſtrong man in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Theſe three have as by a line the word laid out to them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29. baptized for the deads, the ſpirit, the ſoule, the body <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> if the deads are not altogether raiſed, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Hence <hi>Paul</hi> taught the <hi>Corinthians</hi> not as ſpiritual, but carnal, as babes in Chriſt where there are ſet out ſpiritual, and carnal, the carnal babes in Chriſt 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 3. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.10, 11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hence Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I have many things to ſay, but yee cannot bear them now.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 This beginning is ſet out, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. If ye by the Spirit do mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the deeds of the fleſh ye ſhall live. <hi>ver.</hi> 23. The firſt fruits of the ſpirit, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. to the end, and cap. 3. to the end of the 11. where wrath, uncleanneſſe, covetouſneſſe, lying, &amp;c. are ſpoken of, and thus the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> firſt Epiſtle is againſt anger, malice, uncleanneſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The Scriptures ſpeakes of the new creature, which God as in the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48357:27"/>beginning begins with the <hi>Adams</hi> creation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15, 17. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. is the ſpirit, ver: 24. the ſoule, ver. 25. the body.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.</p>
               <p>Irenaeus Lib 5. Cap. ult.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Commoratus eſt Dominus ſanctorum mortuorum ſuorum corum qui ante dormierunt in terram ſtipulationis, &amp; deſcendit ad cos extrahere eos &amp; ſalvare eos, &amp;c.</hi> and after:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſcendit, quid eſt autem niſi quia &amp; deſcendit in inferiora terrae? hoc &amp;</hi> David <hi>in eum prophetans dixit, &amp; eripuiſti animam meam ex infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no inferiori, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Si ergo Dominus legem mortuorum ſervavit ut fieret primo-genitus à mortuis, commoratus uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in tertiam diem in inferioribus terrae, poſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde ſurgens in carne, ut etiam figuras clavoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ostenderet diſcipulis, ſit aſcendit ad patrem, quomodo non confundenter qui di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt inferos qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eſſe hunc mundum qui ſit ſecundum nos, interiorem autem hominem ipſorum derelinquentem hic corpus, in ſupercaelestem aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendere locum, cum enim dominus in medio umbrae mortis abierit ubi animae mortuorum erant, poſt deinde corporaliter reſurrexit, &amp; poſt reſurrectionem aſſumptus eſt, manifeſtum eſt, quia &amp; diſcipulorum ejus propter quos &amp; haec operatus eſt Dominus, animae abibunt in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibilem locum definitum eis a Deo, &amp; ibi uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad reſurrectionem com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morabuntur ſuſtinentes reſurrectionem. Poſt recipientes corpora, &amp; perfecte reſurgentes, hoc eſt corporaliter, quemadmodum &amp; dominus reſurrexit, ſic veniet ad conſpectum Dei. Nemo enim eſt diſcipulus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per magiſtrum; perfectus autem omnis erit ſicut magister ejus. Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ergo magiſter noster non ſtatim evolans abiit, ſed ſuſtinens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitum a patre reſurrectionis ſuae tempus, quod &amp; per Jonam mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtum eſt, post triduum reſurgens aſſumpted eſt, ſic &amp; nos ſuſtinere debemus àd definitum a Deo reſurrectionis noſtrae tempus praenunciatum à prophetis, &amp; ſic reſurgentes aſſumi quotquot Dominus hoc dignos ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſence of the latter part is this.</p>
               <p>If therefore the Lord kept the law of the dead, that he might become the firſt begotten from the dead, and abode in the lower parts of the earth untill the third day, and then after ariſing in the fleſh, that alſo he might ſhew to his Diſciples the figures of the keys, he foraſcendeth to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo that they ſhould not be confounded who affirm hell to be this world, which to us is ſo, but here the body forſaking <hi>the inward man,</hi> it aſcends into a ſuper-celeſtial place, (that is the Spirit.) For when the Lord departed in the middeſt of the ſhadow of death, where the ſoules
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48357:27"/>of the dead were, he after aroſe bodily, and after his reſurrection aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; as is manifeſt, becauſe the ſoules of his Diſciples, for whom the Lord did theſe things, departed into an inviſible place appointed them of God, and there are to remain untill the reſurrection, expecting it after receiving their bodies, they perfectly ariſe, that is, bodily, as the Lord aroſe, and ſo ſhall come into the ſight of the Lord. No Diſciple is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his Maſter, but will be perfect, if he be as his Maſter; as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Maſter forthwith did not fly forth and depart, but bearing the appointed time of his reſurrection from the Father; which was alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by <hi>Jonas</hi> who ariſing after three daies was taken up, ſo we alſo ought to beare the defined time of our reſurrection ſet of God, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told of the Prophets, and ſo riſing as many as the Lord account worthy to be aſſumed.</p>
               <p>In this yee may ſee how the times neare Chriſt, taught of death and the ſoule, and the ſpirit. I confeſſe I ſaw not this in any of the Fathers, untill I had written what goeth before; many things herein I cannot aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto, though moſt I have, on the Scriptures cited before applyed: the Lord give thee judgement and underſtanding herein, that thou mayſt know the truth and worſhip God therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertull.</hi> ſaith thus of the ſoule in <hi>lib. reſurrect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quaſi nos ſeorſum ab anima ſimus, cum totum quod ſumus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſit. Deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſive anima nihil ſumus ne hominis quidem, ſed cada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veris nomen ſi ergo ignoramus animam ipſa ſe ignorat:</hi> and yet wee know not the ſoule, nor nothing leſſe then it.</p>
               <p>In his book on the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> againſt <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apoſtolus optans ut spiritus noſter &amp; corpus &amp; anima ſine querela in adventu Domini conſerventur, nam &amp; animam poſuit &amp; corpus tam duas res, quam diverſas, licet enim &amp; animae corpus ſit aliquod ſuae qualitatis,</hi> ſicut &amp; ſpiritus. In which I ſuppoſe he ſtrangely erres, and knew little of that which he thought every man that knew any thing, knew very well, the nature of the ſpirit being far differing from the ſoule, as the ſoule from the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>De Reſurrectione habet enim de ſuo ſolummodo cogitare, velle cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, disponere ad perficiendum operam carnis expectat; ſic ad pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum ſocietatem carnis expoſtulat, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ireneus Lib 5. Cap. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suo igitur ſanguine redimente nos Domine, &amp; dante animam ſuam pro anima noſtra, &amp; carnem ſuam pro nostris carnibus, &amp; effundente ſpiritum patris, in admiſſionem &amp; communionem Dei &amp; hominum, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:48357:28"/>
               <p>Ibid. <hi>Ut ab initio plaſmationis noſtrae in</hi> Adam, <hi>eaquae fuit â Deo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratio vitae unita plaſmati animavit hominem, &amp; Animal rationabile oſtendit; ſic in fine verbum patris &amp; spiritus Dei adunit us antiquae ſubſtantiae plaſmationis Adae viventem, &amp; perfectum efficit hominem capientem, mortui ſumus ſic in ſpirituali omnes vivificemur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ibid. <hi>Si mortale non vivificat &amp; corruptibile non revocat ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptelam jam non potens eſt Deus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Idem. <hi>Perfecius autem homo, commixio &amp; adunitio eſt animae aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis ſpiritum patris, &amp; admixtae in carne, quae eſt plaſma ſecundum imaginem Dei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ibid. <hi>Cum autem spiritus hic commixtus animae, unitur plaſmati, propter effuſionem spiritus, spiritualis &amp; perfectus homo factus eſt, &amp; hic eſt qui ſecundum imaginem &amp; ſimilitudinem Dei factus eſt; ſi autem defuerit animae spiritus, animalis eſt vere qui eſt talis &amp; carnalis, derelictus, imperfectus eſt, imaginem quidem habens in plaſmate ſimilitudinem vero non aſſumens per spiritum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Idem. <hi>Sunt ex quibus perfectus homo conſtat carne, anima, spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ibidem. <hi>Quid eſt, aut quid, ut granum tritici ſeminatur &amp; putrit in terra niſi, corpora quae in terr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ponuntur, in qua &amp; ſemina jactantur, &amp; propter hoc dixit, ſeminatur in ignobilitate &amp; ſurgit in gloria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Idem. <hi>Quemadmodum enim corruptelae eſt capax caro, ſic &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptelae, &amp; quemadmodum mortis, ſic &amp; vitae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the two Opinions of the ſoule.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Whether the ſoule dyeth and lyeth with the body in the grave.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether it ſleep in the body, as the life in the ſeed ſown.</p>
               <p>There is no deſtruction of the faith whether we underſtand one or the other.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe both agree that it is in the grave.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Sleep and death are as one to it, ſleep is <hi>imago mortis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Both agree that it injoys not God for the time of its being in the grave.</p>
               <p n="4">4 That it is with the body to partake of the reſurrection, if it bee dead it muſt be quickened, and that as the mortall body, if aſleep then it muſt be awakened.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen de principiis de anima, Lib.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haec de rationali anima diſcutienda magis à legentibus quamſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta &amp; definitia protulimus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:48357:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hierm Ep. to Vigilan Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God is not the God of the dead but of the living,</hi> Mark. 12. I am the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which he applies to the ſoule, but indeed is more proper to the ſpirit, now of the ſoule he uſeth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. <hi>Ais enim in ſinu Abrabae vel in loco refrigerii, vel ſubter aram Dei, animas Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolorum, vel Martyrum conſediſſe, nec poſſe ſuiis tumulis &amp; ubi vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerint adeſſe praeſentes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Thoſe men whoſe bodies were burned, given to beaſts, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; not buried; their ſoules as wanting the grave and place of reſt for ſouls; are ſaid to be under the Altar.</p>
               <p n="2">2 No other ſouls have that benefit, but reſt with their bodies.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The reaſon, Becauſe they are not in the grave, and with their body, or in Heaven, where they would be.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Have they no better place for the ſpirit, which the Scripture ſaith is with God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clemenſ. Ep.</hi> on <hi>James</hi> alludes to this, but is ſtrangely corrupted, ſo as not fit to be cited; he tels that as a reward of God, <hi>Enoch</hi> that was found juſt remained longer in the body, others tranſlated to Paradice; others not ſo juſt, their bodies are diſſolved, but ſouls in pleaſant places, that in the reſurrection of the dead, their bodies ſhould receive and injoy the eternall inheritance.</p>
               <p>And here, becauſe of what my adverſaries may clandeſtinely abuſe me, and the truth, calling it <hi>Socinianiſm, Arminianiſm,</hi> or the like. Note I declare againſt their doctrine.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That what now men againſt the Scriptures among us, falſly attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the ſoule, that I hold is in Scripture given to the ſpirit, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers at its departure out of the body by the death of the ſoule, weal with God, or woe with Satan and ſinners.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſouls of good and bad, whiles dead or a ſleep, remain ſo until the reſurrection of the body at the laſt day.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That good and bad then ſhall in ſoule, body, and ſpirit, be raiſed, united, and judged by Jeſus Chriſt and ſuffer in all evill of pain and loſſe, if reprobates; and injoy bleſſedneſſe, and joy, if they belong to Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</p>
               <p n="4">4 It ſhall be the ſame body, ſoule, and ſpirit, and not others, againſt the Doctrine of the <hi>Remonſtants</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> which I could ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prove, but that it is not my purpoſe at this time to ſpeak any more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, then to prevent offences and ſcandals that may ariſe either through the diſaffection or miſ underſtanding of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:48357:29"/>
               <head>To underſtand what the Spirit of Chriſt is to us, by the help of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence of the God-head, aſſiſting the ſame thereunto, is of ſpeciall concernment.</head>
               <p n="1">1 CHriſt ſpeaking of his humane ſpirit ſaith, <hi>Job.</hi> 6.63. <hi>It is the Spirit quickeneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing;</hi> here by Spirit is meant that more excellent part of the humane nature, in Scripture oppoſed to fleſh.</p>
               <p n="2">2 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45, <hi>The firſt man</hi> Adam (by ſin) <hi>came to be a living ſoule, the laſt</hi> Adam <hi>a live-making ſpirit,</hi> Chriſt being made and fitted of God on purpoſe, to quicken the ſpirits of men dead in them, by <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, in which the great myſtery of the Goſpel is hid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.21. As the Father raiſeth and maketh alive the dead, which was Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.15. and 4.10. and 5.30. and 13.30. whom God made a quickening Spirit, and raiſed his dead ſoule and body from their ſeveral deaths.</p>
               <p>So the Son maketh alive whom he will, which is the ſpirituall work of Chriſts ſpirit on the ſpirits of the Elect, with which compare, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21. <hi>As by man came death, alſo by man came the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead.</hi> Ver. 22. <hi>As in</hi> Adam <hi>all dye, ſo in Christ ſhall all be made alive;</hi> to whom as Mediator before the giving up of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, death ſhall be done away and put under his feet, in which is the utter overthrow of death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to return.</p>
               <p>John. 5.26. <hi>As the Father hath life in himſelfe</hi> (in the raiſing of Chriſt) <hi>ſo he gave the Son to have life in himſelfe.</hi> Ver. 24. <hi>That whoſoever beleeveth in him that ſent him, and heareth his word might have eternal life; and not come into judgement, but hath paſſed from death unto life;</hi> which of neceſſity muſt be meant of the ſpirits death and quickening.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Note, This quickening of the ſpirit, and paſſing from death to life, is called the firſt reſurrection, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.5. It being the ſole work of Chriſt in the time of grace, to quicken the ſpirits of the Elect, and to make them partakers of this firſt reſurrection, which precedes that of the ſoul and body; ſo that the reſurrection which men have by the ſoule and body of Chriſt at the laſt day, is no profit to that man, who is not firſt rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or quickened by the ſpirit, to the firſt reſurrection.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:48357:29"/>2 This is opened 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Knowing he who raiſed the Lord Jeſus, alſo doth raiſe us by Jeſus, and ſhall preſent us with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Yee are not in the fleſh but in the ſpirit, if the spirit of God dwell in you, but if any have not the spirit of Christ, he is none of his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 You have the Spirit of God ſaid to dwel in men.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The having of the Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Without the one, man cannot pleaſe God; without the other, he is not Chriſts.</p>
               <p>Ver. 14. <hi>Thoſe are led by the Spirit of God, are the Sons of God.</hi> Gal. 4.6. <hi>Into whoſe hearts becauſe they are Sons, God by his Spirit ſends forth the Spirit of his Son, teaching them to cry abba Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Spirit of God is uſually called the Spirit of promiſe (the Spirit, the holy) which we read the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of God given as a ſeale of the grace of God in Chriſt to man, and the worke done on them.</p>
               <p>Rom. 8.26. <hi>The spirit alſo helpeth our infirmities for wee know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought; but the Spirit it ſelfe maketh interceſſion for us with groans that cannot be uttered,</hi> Ver. 27. <hi>He that ſearcheth the heart knoweth what is in the mind of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, becauſe he makes interceſſion for the Saints according to the will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note, Where by the Spirit, and Spirit it ſelfe, the Spirit of Chriſt, ſent forth of God into the hearts of Saints, be not intended, is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to your judgements to conſider of, or where the Spirit, the Holy.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe here is no eſpecial epithite to it, as uſually given to God the Spirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It is the ſpirit of interceſſion, which is the Spirit of Chriſt, ſtirring up in us ſighs and groans, as in him.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Bearing our infirmities, which is done by Chriſt as man, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15. and c. 5 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 9 4.</p>
               <p n="4">4 God the ſearcher of the heart, is put as diſtinct from the Spirit of Chriſt in the heart, who is ſaid to intercede according to the Will of God.</p>
               <p n="5">5 This Spirit is not ours, as it is not Gods, for ſaith he, <hi>Wee know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought;</hi> whereby <hi>we,</hi> is meant, the whole regenerate man, who without Chriſts Spirit aſſiſt him in prayer, knows not how to pray, nor for what to pray as he ought.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:48357:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Appli.</hi> If this be truth, the Doctrine taught makes Chriſt void, and in him God is put off from us, becauſe none can come to the Father but by him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Illust.</hi> To ſet before your eyes the ſpirits reſurrection, ſee it fulfilled in <hi>Cyrus</hi> a heathen lying under a dead ſpirit, when quickened, works wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.15. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.22. he is not that man he was before.</p>
               <p>The excellency of Chriſts Spirits operation in the Elect, is wonderful and precious.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The Spirit of life in Jeſus Chriſt gave the new Law or Covenant (as <hi>Moſes</hi> the Mediator of the Old gave that) by which we are freed from <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, called the Law of <hi>ſin and death, Rom.</hi> 8.2.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It is called the Law of the ſpirit of life.</p>
               <p n="1">1 None being under this Law, untill quickened by the Spirit of life, but were under the law of death.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It is the law of the ſpirit of life, in which thoſe made alive muſt walk in, and live under it, as its Law, as <hi>Moſes</hi> Diſciples under its.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This Law was for the ſpirit to walke with God in; when men are ſaid to walk in the ſpirit, and live in the ſpirit, when men are onely ſaid to pleaſe God.</p>
               <p n="4">4 That this is meant of ours, and Chriſts Spirit, becauſe oppoſed to the fleſh, which cannot walke in this Law. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8.</p>
               <p>Note, It is one means by which the Spirit of Chriſt is diſtinguiſhed from God the Spirit, is that which commeth by hearing, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2, 5. which differs far from that <hi>Act.</hi> 10.44. called the Holy Ghoſt, ſaid to fall on them, having the gift of tongues.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of God after is given for confirmation of ſuch as doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30. and manifeſted it ſelfe in dreams, viſions, tongues, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning of ſpirits, propheſie.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of Chriſt worketh faith, love, deſires, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. which <hi>Origen</hi> would have to be meant of the regenerate mans own Spirit, which indeed is a fruit of the Spirit of Chriſt in us; for of our ſelves we are not able to think a good thought, It <hi>is Chriſt that worketh all in all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Illuſt. Act.</hi> 8.12. People of <hi>Samaria,</hi> Beleeved <hi>Phillip</hi> which was the act of the ſpirit of Chriſt in them, who yet <hi>ver.</hi> 16. are ſaid none of them to have received the Holy Ghoſt; though by the firſt the Spirit of Chriſt they were baptized and ſo ſaid to be Chriſts, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. after which <hi>ver.</hi> 17. they were eſtabliſhed having the Holy Spirit powred out upon them, by the laying on of hands by the Apoſtle, the one is mediately by hearing given men, the other, ſince the Apoſtles daies immediately of God.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:48357:30"/>1 To this being of Chriſt in his Spirit in the Saints, the Apoſtle emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently alludes, ſaying, <hi>Chriſt in you is the hope of glory,</hi> as <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. now if he have the Spirit of God in him, God is in him; if of Chriſt, Chriſt is in him.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By the Spirit of Chriſt, before he hath the Spirit of God in him, he hath the hope of glory, but not the ſeale of glory, which diſtinguiſheth the ſpirits in their diſtinct operations.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thus the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Since yee ſeeke a proofe of Chriſt ſpeaking in me, which to you ward is not weak, but is mighty in you,</hi> Ver. 5. <hi>Know you not Jeſus Chriſt is in you except you be Reprobates;</hi> Rom. 8.9, 10. <hi>If any have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his. And if Chriſt be in you</hi> (that is, by his Spirit, as before) <hi>the body is dead becauſe of ſinne, but the ſpirit</hi> (that is, mans ſpirit) <hi>is life</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quickened)) <hi>becauſe of righteouſneſſe.</hi> Gal. 2.20. <hi>I live, yet not I but Chriſt liveth in me; the life that I now live is by faith in the Son of God,</hi> which comes by hearing, and is an effect of the Spirit of Chriſt, ſent out of God the Spirit, as well as Father, unto the heart of ſons <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. Chriſt lives in the heart by faith.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The uſe of this ſpirit is hinted at, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.19. <hi>This ſhall turn to my ſalvation through your prayers and the ſupply of the Spirit of Chriſt.</hi> Phil. 4.13. <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt that strengtheneth me, Act.</hi> 16.7. Some tranſlations read, <hi>The Spirit of Jeſus ſuffered them not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Except a man be born of Water and of the Spirit hee cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> Here by Spirit, I underſtand the Spirit of Chriſt, by which he is one Spirit with the Lord, and grafted unto him by baptiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. It is not ſaid the Holy Spirit, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Spirit only, as before.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Ver.</hi> 12. In this ſaying, Chriſt tels them, he told them of earthly things, it being to be done by the quickening Spirit of Chriſts humanity aſſiſted thereunto by his divine power.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Hence it is the Scripture ſaith, <hi>he that is in Chriſt is a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. That is born of the Spirit, ſignifies, that regeneration is by Chriſts Spirit onely, not of our Spirits. The Spirit of Chriſt work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith and Obedience to Chriſt in Baptiſme, in which is regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:48357:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Application</hi> 1. Men are taught that there is no other Spirit, but God the Spirit who worketh theſe; and all that have any of theſe, have the gift of the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Spirit of Chriſt which worketh theſe, is not known, men oppoſe againſt it, and deny it to be, who yet would be Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Hence, as Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, ſo the men of this age know not what ſpirits they are of, that have the Spirit of Chriſt in them, and not the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Few men have the Spirit of God, and they that have it, have it in a hidden way which is by dreams and viſions; being all that, as I know of, as yet accompanies the gift of the Spirit of God in theſe daies; to which I might ſay ſomething, or may do when this generation is made fit for it, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17, 18. By which men ſhall propheſie, I ſpeak not this to glory in, but to glorifie God in it, and in his accompliſhing his truth, of which <hi>Huſſe</hi> had ſweet experiences, as his Letters teſtifies cited by <hi>Fox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 I ſpeak not this to countenance any fancies or corruptions among men, <hi>try the ſpirits if they are of God.</hi> Therefore</p>
               <p n="2">2 I ſpeak it, that men take heed leaſt they ſcoffe at the grace of God, and his gifts, as thoſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.13. a worke which is done to the griefe of the ſpirit in groſſe manner amongſt us, and that among the learned, for which, as a judgement it is kept from the world, and men hindred from looking to God for it.</p>
               <p n="3">3 I ſpeak it to incourage thoſe that have it, to ſee if they have the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, and then to look on this as the ſeale of God, to that Chriſt hath done in thee, and on thee, to thy exceeding joy.</p>
               <p n="4">4 When God ſhall reſtore the Church, and this glorious mercy in its glory to men, how will they then wonder at the enmity and evil that was in the world reigning among thoſe men who profeſſed themſelves Saints, and Sons of God, having the ſpirit in them.</p>
               <p>Note, Becauſe man is carnall and needs helps even in theſe, that are, comparatively, but earthly things, compared with other divine myſteries of God and Chriſt, I commend theſe conſiderations,</p>
               <p n="1">1 The unknown excellency of the ſpirit of a man, as in <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3, 4. <hi>For I verily as abſent in body but preſent in ſpirit, have judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed already as though I were preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note, Though abſent in body, yet was he preſent in ſpirit, though his body (being at <hi>Phillippi</hi>) was one hundred of miles from them.</p>
               <p n="2">2 His preſence in ſpirit was ſuch, as that it was as ſufficient as if he had been bodily judging the man with them.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:48357:31"/>
               <p>Verſ. 4. <hi>In the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, when you are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, and my ſpirit with the power of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Coloſ. 2.5. <hi>For though I am abſent in the fleſh, yet am I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Spirit with you</hi> (a place in which <hi>Paul</hi> never was, ver. 1.) <hi>joying, and beholding your order and ſtedfaſtneſſe of faith in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now thus far the ſpirit of a man may doe, even be preſent with men afar off from his body, and joy in their good, and ſuffer in their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, though it can but look on it, it is the Spirit of the Lord Jeſus that acts in and over all onely, who is not onely a ſpectator or ſtander by in his ſpirituall preſence among the Saints, but walks among the ſeven golden Candleſticks, and acts, and knocks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.32. <hi>The ſpirit of the Prophets is ſubject to the Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt Concluſion, That there is a notable place here, to ſay with <hi>Solomon, Who knoweth the ſpirit of a man,</hi> Eccleſ. 3.21.</p>
               <p n="2">2 If in the ſpirit of man is ſuch an unknown excellency, how then is the Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 God making Chriſt and fitting him with ſuch a Spirit, by which he might raiſe the dead ſpirit, and communicate himſelfe to it, and be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way preſent with it, through the operation and aſſiſtance of the infinite God dwelling in him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. ver. 45. God making this the end of making Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.23.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whiles Chriſt <hi>John</hi> 17.11. ſaith, I am no more in the world, that is, in ſoule and body, yet he ſaith, ver. 23. <hi>I in them, and thou in me,</hi> which muſt be in his Spirit, ſpeaking of himſelfe as diſtinct from God, in the perſon of the Mediator.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the naturall ſpirits of Men.</head>
               <p>THeſe are differing in themſelves (the bodies differ not in height, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſtrength, in quality and condition of conſtitution, as a Gyant from a Dwrafe, as a ſtrong man differs from him that is never ſo weak, and the moſt beautifull and perſonable man differs not from the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Blackmore,) ſo much as one natural mans ſpirit from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:48357:32"/>
               <p>Some are ſtrong, ſome weak; ſome raſh, ſome patient; ſome proud, ſome humble; ſome cruel, ſome meek; ſome well, ſome ſick; ſome high ſome low.</p>
               <p>In which corruptly remain the appearances of the ſeven Spirits of God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.2. Wiſdom, Might, Knowledge, Underſtanding, as a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to receive them, or the Spirit of Chriſt, in whom all theſe treaſures are.</p>
               <p>Of whoſe unknown worth the Scriptures ſpeak, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Who knoweth the ſpirit of a man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eccleſ. 11.5. <hi>There is not to thee the knowledge of the way of the ſpirit, nor how the bones of him doth grow that are in the womb,</hi> &amp;c. which proves it is ſpoke of the naturall ſpirit of man.</p>
               <p>Note it clears that objection that may be made, <hi>How doth the ſpirit of a man, his body being in one place, come to be in another;</hi> And ſhews.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The ſpirit hath a way of its own, that the body hath not.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The way of it is unknown to any, even the wiſeſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Eſpecially to thoſe who know not that they have a ſpirit at all in them.</p>
               <p n="4">4 To all ſuch, who though they know they have it in them, yet it is dead, and never found the uſe of them.</p>
               <p>Note, The uſe of the ſpirit is excellent, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. it being the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of naturall man that bears his infirmities, as the Spirit of Chriſt in the beleever bears his.</p>
               <p>The good man is ſaid to have another ſpirit, as differing from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural mans, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.24. compared with Chap. 13.30, 31. ſhew how the ſpirit in a man doth change him and make him differ from others.</p>
               <p>It is a great queſtion may bee made, Whether Chriſts humane Spirit was not in being before it was joyned to the fleſh, ſoule, in the Virgins wombe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. The Spirit of Chriſt is ſaid to have been in the Prophets of old, which is that part of the Lord which was oynted, as diſtinct from the anointing of the Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe it is ſaid, the ſpirit of Chriſt is the ſpirit of Propheſie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>John</hi> 3.13. The Son of man, is ſaid, as man, to come down from heaven, which was that part of him called his Spirit, which alſo now whiles he is on earth, is ſaid to be in heaven, as the Son of man.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The God-head cannot be ſaid to go <hi>a loce, ad locum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 The Scripture ſpeaks of Chriſt in his being to the Saints long before his incarnation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:48357:32"/>6 How Chriſt is <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. <hi>He which is, and was, and is to come,</hi> &amp;c. ver. 8. that he is <hi>Alpha and Omega.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 That he is the firſt fruits, and the foundation of the Church.</p>
               <p n="8">8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; How he is ſaid to be from heaven, and in what? and how to be the ſecond Man? and whether he had not in ſpirit a being when firſt promiſed <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>Before</hi> Abraham <hi>was I am, ſaith the Lord,</hi> ſpeaking as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.58. Verſ. 56. <hi>Abraham rejoyced to ſee my day and ſaw it, and was glad,</hi> Ver. 57. <hi>Thou art not fifty years old, and haſt thou ſeen</hi> Abraham? that this is only fulfilled in the Divine nature of Chriſt is the queſtion.</p>
               <p n="10">10 The Rabbies underſtand, that alway the word <hi>Adonai</hi> is diſtinct in the Old Teſtament from <hi>Jehova</hi> in the perſons ſignified by them, God, and Chriſt, unleſſe ſome other divine Epithite be added.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That it was the Lord Chriſt appeared in the form of man before he had fleſh.</p>
               <p n="12">12 He is ſaid to be <hi>the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever;</hi> he was man yeſterday, by having mans ſpirit before he took fleſh, and when he had fleſh, and ſince, <hi>viz.</hi> that is, the Lord was Mediator for poor man before and ſince, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8. he was in fleſh among us.</p>
               <p n="13">13 He is ſaid to be the beginning of the creation of God, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.14.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Nor is it any where ſaid, God inſpired into him his Spirit, but the Spirit overſhadowed the Virgin, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.35.</p>
               <p>Object. 2 Cor. 11.4. <hi>For if he that commeth preacheth another Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus whom we have not preached, or if yee receive another spirit which we have not received, or another Goſpel which yee have not accepted, yee might well bear with him;</hi> ſo that it ſeems the ſpirit Chriſtians have is but one.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. He ſpeaks of the preaching Jeſus.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The receiving the Spirit by that preaching.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That that was preached of Jeſus was the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Note, Which ſhews, that the Spirit here, was that came by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and by that means was ordinarily received, which was the Spirit of Chriſt, not that called the Holy Spirit of God, which is alſo one Spirit proper to the perſon of Chriſt, for excellency, power, life, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That the Spirit of God and Chriſt in Scripture are variouſly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, I have proved before.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:48357:33"/>4 Chriſt was not man without the one, nor God without the other.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The work of the God-head in Chriſt, was to make effectuall the work of the Spirit to man, that was humane in him.</p>
               <p>Hence is he ſaid to offer up himſelf on the eternal ſpirit to God, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing God the Spirit in him from that ſpirit of man in himſelfe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.8.</p>
               <p n="6">6 To adde one place more for diſtinction, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Why hath Satan filled thy heart to lie to the Holy Ghost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ver. 10. <hi>How is it that yee have agreed together to tempt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Annanias</hi> bringing not the full price after he had promiſed it to God, and ſaying, it was the whole to the Church, brake his vow to God, and lyed to the Holy Spirit; he being by the Spirit moved hereto, to a ſpiritual end.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saphira</hi> being privy to the deceit onely, but did not come with it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church with her Husband; the evill of the fact was mainly in her Husband; again, had ſhe not been demanded, ſhe would, it is like, have been ſilent in it, the Text onely ſaith ſhe was privy to it, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Note hence, the Word ſaith, the being privy, and the concealment of the fact was a tempting of the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Note, The lying to the Holy Spirit was a more dreadful evill of a higher nature, more immediately againſt God, then this of tempting the Spirit of the Lord; In the leſſer evill was one, in the greater the other; in the private the one, in the publick ſin the other.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Note, Satan filled <hi>Annanias</hi> heart, but after that <hi>Annanias</hi> tempted <hi>Saphira,</hi> who agree together to tempt the Spirit of the Lord, <hi>Mark.</hi> 2.8.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Note, Here is the ground of the fearfulneſſe of the judgement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was committed againſt the Spirit of God and Chriſt, and their operations in them.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>John</hi> 1.13. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. and 4.7. and 5.1.4.18. <hi>Men are ſaid to be born of God, therefore the Spirit</hi> Joh. 3.5. <hi>muſt be by the Spirit of God, which is the Spirit of Chriſt, and cannot be underſtood that the humane ſpirit of Chriſt, hath any hand herein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Theſe are excellently diſtinguiſhed and cleared, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. by the waſhing of regeneration: Mark, there is water and the Spirit of Chriſt, for without the Spirit can be no regeneration.</p>
               <p n="2">2 He comes and after tells us of renewing of the Holy Spirit, when
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48357:33"/>the Spirit of God renews in man in a more divine way, this their rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration in them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. beleevers are to be renewed in the Spirit of their mind.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In the work of the Spirit of Chriſt, they are ſaid to be Chriſts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. and having the Spirit of God, Gods, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4 18. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13</p>
               <p n="4">4 Theſe are more clearly ſpoke of, and joyned together, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.10. all mine, that have the worke of my Spirit quickening them, are thine, thy Spirit renewing that Spirit of the mind within them.</p>
               <p n="5">5 That of <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. of being born from above is one thing; that of verſ. 5. is another, of being born of water and the Spirit.</p>
               <p n="1">1 By the one, men ſee the Kingdom of God, verſ. 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By the other, men enter the Kingdom, verſ. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Verſ. 12. diſtinguiſh them, that are Verſ. 5. ſaid to be earthly things, becauſe done on earth by the Spirit of the Lord in the uſe of means, and not comparable, for it is divine Nature and glory, with the other.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The other is from above, that is, God and Heaven, and called in compariſon hereof heavenly things.</p>
               <p>Object. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. <hi>No man ſpeaking in the Spirit of God ſaith, Jeſus is accurſed; nor is any able to call Jeſus Lord, but in the Holy Spirit, therefore it is the Holy Spirit men are born of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Here is ſpoken of the firſt part of Gods Spirit on man, which is to diſcover the things of the Kingdome, that ſo they be brought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve them, without which they call not Chriſt Lord, and having this they cannot diſpiſe the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By which beleeving, the Spirit of Chriſt is introduced.</p>
               <p n="3">3 After all which, the beleevers being baptized, the Spirit was given to renew that Spirit of the mind that was in them, by which the things of God came to be apprehended more divinely and clearly; thus, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples after their knowing Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26. by the Spirit knew him more divinely.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of Chriſt perfects in men, the image of the Lord in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of his converſation to the Goſpel, <hi>be ye followers of me as I am of Chriſt, and learn of me, ſaith the Lord Jeſus, I am humble and meek.</hi> which is called a putting on of Chriſt,</p>
               <p>The Spirit of Chriſt quickens the ſpirit, when the Spirit of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes in man the image of God loſt, and again indues him with his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by which he is a new creature to his God, Hence <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.4. <hi>When Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, &amp;c.</hi> Verſ. 3. <hi>Our life is hid
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48357:34"/>with Chriſt;</hi> before he ſays they were dead (that is with Chriſt) and now are alive with Chriſt, and their life was hid with Chriſts life, which lived in them, and quickened them, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> clears by his manner of ſpeaking, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I live</hi> (that is, ſpiritually, which as if he had ſaid amiſſe, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain corrects, with a) <hi>yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me, and the life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by faith in the Son of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note, in this to the full is opened that <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.17. <hi>My Father workes hereunto, and I worke,</hi> Verſ. 19. <hi>The Son can do nothing of himſelfe, but what he ſeeth the Father do, whatever he doth, thoſe things alſo doth the Son.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſ. 21. <hi>As the Father raiſeth up the dead and quickeneth them, even ſo the Son quickeneth whom he will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſ. 26. <hi>As the Father hath life in himſelfe, ſo hath he given to the Sonne to have life in himſelfe,</hi> that was in the Spirit of his mind, Hence <hi>he laid down his life, and had power to take it again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note, <hi>Moſes</hi> had not the leſſe of the Spirit, by what the ſeventy had; nor Chriſt, by what the elect have, the fountaine is ever full.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Illuſt.</hi> If as in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.20, 21. one ſpirit is a lying ſpirit in the mouth of all <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prophets; how much more ſhall the Spirit of Chriſt be in, and direct all the elect of God.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>That was an Angelicall Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> The ſpirit of man was of an Angelical nature, having no fleſh, nor bones; yea if the Angels were created <hi>ex prima materia,</hi> as moſt hold, it may be of a more excellent nature then they, being breathed of God into man, by which man is called the off-ſpring of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Spirit of Chriſt, as joyned to the Spirit of God, and ſent out of God into the hearts of his Elect, by far exceeds the Angels (who have their dependance on him as on their head) in the power and way he hath of communicating it ſelfe to men.</p>
               <p n="3">3 By this, God makes the Spirit of the Man Chriſt, with his ſoul and body, to be a root, a ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> by which beleevers receive life in ſpirit from him, as death from <hi>Adam;</hi> without Gods aſſiſtance, the Spirit of Chriſt cannot be in mine, nor work on mine at all.</p>
               <p>Objections made by Mr.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>That ſoul and ſpirit were expreſſed</hi> exegeticos, <hi>and that they are but one, though they had two names.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> That to maintain theſe two to be one, againſt the expreſſe word
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48357:34"/>of God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>John</hi> 12.10. is hereſie, <hi>Luk. i.</hi> 46.47. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.46. with <hi>Act.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Offering the teſtimony of <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.46, 47. he ſaid, <hi>That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it was read my ſoule, and my ſpirit, it may be read, my ſoul my, ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> To put down ſoule for ſpirit, the word ſoule being before, was to take away from the Word of God, and to be liable to the curſe of God; yea, to be accurſed, though an Angel.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>The ſpirit of man is the Spirit of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Was <hi>My</hi> that, that was blaſphemy becauſe God the Spirit is ſaid to be one with the created ſpirit of man, ſinfull, filthy, dead.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe in haſt I ſaid, that the Spirit. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. was the Spirit of God, which is meant the ſpirit of man quickened by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What the diſtinct difference was between the spirit and ſoul of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp. Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 3.21. who knoweth the ſpirit of a man, with whoſe death the knowledge of it dyed alſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Yet a more apparent difference to diſtinguiſh them cannot be, then this, that the one (the ſpirit) hath its being imediately from God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. the other (the ſoule) from man, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.10.</p>
               <p n="3">3 They in the diſſolution of the fabrick of Man, are diſtinguiſhed the ſpirit returning to God, the ſoule to the grave.</p>
               <p>Note, So that to affirm ſoule and ſpirit to be one, I declared to be falſe doctrine, and the Teachers, falſe Teachers that taught it.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.8. <hi>God breathed into man the breath of life: Man therefore had but one life, which was his ſoul life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> The word is corruptly tranſlated, it is not <hi>life,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>lives,</hi> and ſo the ſpirit life is comprehended under the ſame word.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>After it is ſaid, and man became a living ſoul, therefore man had no other but a ſoule in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> The words are thus to be read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the <hi>Adam the body, was for the living ſoule,</hi> which had but one of the lives, the body being to the ſoule, eſpecially it being near to it, partaking with it in eating, drinking, ſuffering <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which the ſpirit doth not, but is of a more ſublime, and excellent nature.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The ſoule comes from man with the body, in its beginning.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It goeth to the grave with the body in its ending.</p>
               <p n="3">3 It is not ſaid, the <hi>Adam</hi> was for the ſouls life, as before.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:48357:35"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.27. <hi>Mark.</hi> 12.30. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.27. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy ſoule, with all thy mind, with all thy ſtrength,</hi> which is the body, which the ſoule, which the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. The Queſtion is propounded concerning a command of the law, which command was given after mans fall by ſin, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits death.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The commands were given the fleſhy part of man, whence it is ſaid, <hi>by the Law no fleſh living can be juſtified, Ezek.</hi> 20.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Hence for the ſpirit of man, it could have no releife by the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. it could not make alive, that is, the dead ſpirit, as Chriſt was to do, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. What the Law ſpeaks, it ſpeaks to them under the Law.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The ſpirit when alive, it was not under any dominion of the Law, man then was a law to himſelfe, he needed none, nor was any given untill two thouſand years after mans fall.</p>
               <p n="2">2 When it was dead it was under none, for <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.1. <hi>The Law hath dominion over a man onely whiles alive,</hi> not when dead; therefore Chriſt firſt quickeneth the ſpirits before he give them that Law.</p>
               <p n="3">3 When the ſpirit is quickened by Chriſt, it is dead to the Law of the fleſh, and freed, and in ſubjection onely to the Law of the Spirit of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.8. diſtinguiſhed <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Here are not three parts but four, Heart, Mind, Soule, Strength.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Which ſhews that the Spirit, Soule, and Body are not aimed at, as in the other Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That here as the command was given the Naturall man, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the naturall mans parts of Heart, and Soule, Strength, and Mind, are inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and not the Spirit, that was dead in man, and was not capable of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience or command.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>The Law is ſpiritual,</hi> Rom. 7.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> The Law indeed, is ſaid to be ſpiritual, but no where ſaid to be a Law of the Spirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſpirituality of the Law.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Is in mentioning the Name of God, and forbidding Idol-worſhip, and injoyning the love of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It is ſpiritual in condemning coveting.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Yet ſee that God had a mind to the Soule and Body in theſe commands.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:48357:35"/>1 Conſider the preface, <hi>I am the Lord thy God. &amp;c.</hi> in which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of the ſoule and body, not the ſpirit is mentioned.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By this Law men were judged by the Magiſtrate, to whom the ſoul was ſubjected, not the ſpirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Hence <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.20. the ſoule is ſaid to dye by, and to be under this Law.</p>
               <p>I propoſed this to him.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That no Scripture ſaith at death, the ſoule returneth to God, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth immediately to Heaven, before the reſurrection, but that it goeth to the grave.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That no Saint ever commended his ſoule to God at death, but his ſpirit, which is onely ſaid to return to God that gave it, and the <hi>Adam</hi> to the duſt and earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ap.</hi> If the Scripture ſaith in many places, the ſoul goeth to the grave, and in no place, that it immediately goeth to God before the reſurrection, who ſhall aſſert it, and not teach falſe Doctrine, and not teach another Goſpell?</p>
               <p n="2">2 If the Scripture ſaith, at the death of a man, only the ſpirit goeth to God immediately for its judgement; and yet men teach that we have no ſpirit, or make ſoule and ſpirit one, and confound thoſe God hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>To which I add, this moſt weighty Query and Objection may be made; <hi>Since that the ſpirit comes from God, whether then it be polluted or not, as it comes out of Gods hand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp. Adam</hi> ſinning as a general perſon, dyed, not onely in his own ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but brought death on the ſpirits of his whole race, for in <hi>Adam</hi> all dye, whoſe death was in ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hence God giving the Spirit, gives it not poſſeſſed of that ſpiritual life as he gave it to <hi>Adam</hi> in its firſt being, but that it comes into man now deprived of his firſt life and excellency:</p>
               <p n="3">3 That it is thus given dead, appears, in that as a remedy, Chriſt by God is given to man, as a quickening Spirit to reſtore and raiſe the dead ſpirit of man againe.</p>
               <p n="4">4 As <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo Chriſt, is deſigned by grace a generall perſon for good to the Elect of God, as <hi>Adam</hi> was by Juſtice for death to all.</p>
               <p n="5">5 It is clear the ſpirits now created of men (that the grace of God might abound) are not in the capacity <hi>Adams</hi> was before, but in that it was after its fall.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Some will cry out, this is injustice in God, for God to give men a dead spirit, and unbeſeeming God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
